<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The golden chaine of mans saluation, and the fearefull point of hardening, opened and set downe in two seuerall sermons preached before the king. / By Anthony Maxey Batchelar in Diuinitie, and chaplaine to his Majesty in ordinary ...</title>
            <author>Maxey, Anthony, d. 1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00422</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17685.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S94149</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">56572896</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 56572896</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180996</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00422)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180996)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2152:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The golden chaine of mans saluation, and the fearefull point of hardening, opened and set downe in two seuerall sermons preached before the king. / By Anthony Maxey Batchelar in Diuinitie, and chaplaine to his Majesty in ordinary ...</title>
                  <author>Maxey, Anthony, d. 1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Eld for Clement Knight, dwelling in Paules Church-yard, at the signe of the holy Lambe.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Initials; tail-pieces.</note>
                  <note>The second sermon has special t.p. "The second sermon preached before the king"; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Includes owner's bookplate, dated 1860(?) bound in following t.p.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Wales.</note>
                  <note>Contains bibliographical references in marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans VIII, 30 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Exodus X, 20 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180996:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180996:1"/>
            <p>THE Golden Chaine of Mans Saluation, and the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full point of hardening, opened and ſet downe in two ſeuerall ſermons preached before the King.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Anthony Maxey</hi> Batchelar in Diuinitie, and Chaplaine to his Maieſty in ordinary.</p>
            <p>The Poynts handled in the firſt, are theſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Predeſtination.</item>
               <item>Calling.</item>
               <item>Iuſtification.</item>
               <item>Glorifying.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The points handled in the ſecond, are theſe, with additions.</p>
            <list>
               <item>That there is an Hardening.</item>
               <item>That God Hardeneth not.</item>
               <item>How men become hardened.</item>
               <item>Moſt wofull to be Hardened The meanes to auoidit.</item>
            </list>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>G. Eld.</hi> for <hi>Clement Knight,</hi> dwelling in Paules Church-yard, at the ſigne of the holy Lambe. 1606.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:180996:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180996:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <div type="part">
                     <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:180996:3"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:180996:3"/>
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Romans. 8. 30. verſ.</bibl>
                        <q>Moreouer, whom he predeſtinated, them alſo he called: and whom he called, them alſo he iuſtified: and whom he iuſtified, them alſo he glorified.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very Scripture (ſaith the bleſſed<note place="margin">2. T <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> Apoſtle) giuen by inſpiration, is profitable to inſtruct the man of God, and to make him perfect to good works. Yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, if a man ſhould ſeeke vpon pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and line by line, trace the whole body of the ſcripture ouer: of all others, this one ſhort verſe, is moſt diuine, moſt excellent. <hi>Singuli Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mones,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Hi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> cap. 3. Eph.</note> 
                        <hi>Sillabae; apices, puncta, in Diuina ſcriptura ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na ſunt ſenſibus.</hi> In the holy ſcripture euery ſpeech and ſentence, euery verſe, euery point and ſilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is rich in ſenſe, and full of diuine and holy miſteries.</p>
                     <p>So is it here. For the points of doctrine, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth the whole ſumme of our religion: for the manner, it conſiſteth of a ſweet gradation: for the matter, it is full of comfortable inſtruction; for the depth of the vnderſtanding, it hath in it, ſuch ſweet, profound, and heauenly miſteries, that, as
<pb facs="tcp:180996:4"/>
it is written, the head of the Riuer <hi>Nylus</hi> could neuer be found: ſo the height, depth, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall knowledge, which lyeth couched in this whole verſe, in euery point, in euery word it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable, it cannot be ſounded. Concerning the Doctrine.</p>
                     <p>Surely, howſoeuer men do liue at eaſe for a time in this life, and careleſſely paſſe on in this buſie world; yet the eſpeciall and maine point, is the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the Soule, to be aſſured of the life to come: and if a man might bee ſatiſfied therein, then all were well, all were ſure indeede.</p>
                     <p>Alas, this life endeth, and God knoweth howe ſoone, euen this night before to morrow, may my ſoule bee taken from mee: and if I could proue vnto my heart, that God had choſen mee to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, then I ſhould thinke my ſelfe the moſt happie and bleſſed creature aliue. In this great and weighty point of ſaluation, for euer, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere a man throughlie and ſoundly, to ſatiſfie a mans heart and ſoule vnto the full, there is no one place in all the holy booke of God, that can, ſo briefely, ſo plainely, ſo ſufficiently inſtruct vs, as this one ſhort verſe.</p>
                     <p>The auncient Fathers, in the courſe of their writings, they doe call it the Golden Chaine of our Saluation, becauſe each one of theſe: <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination, Calling, Iuſtification,</hi> and <hi>Glorifying,</hi> are ſo coupled and knit together, that if you hold fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t
<pb facs="tcp:180996:4"/>
one lincke, you draw vnto you the whole Chaine: if you let go one, you looſe all.</p>
                     <p>For the manner of my proceeding, according to the fathers alluſion: Firſt I wil vnty this Chaine, and weigh euery lincke in his owne proper bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and ſo handling euery point ſeuerally by it ſelfe, in the end I will knit them vp, and cloſe them all together againe. And here before I enter any further, I moſt humbly craue pardon, and fauorable conſtruction in this matter. I know right well, I am to touch a very great and weightye<note place="margin">Pre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> nati <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> part <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> Goſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> prea <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> of, d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> ly a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> uere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> Aug <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> Bon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> point of religion, indeed ſo ſecret and deepe, that I doe throw my ſelfe downe at the foote of Gods mercy ſeat, beſeeching him with all humbleneſſe, to ſupport my weakeneſſe, to enlarge my heart, &amp; to giue me an vnderſtanding ſpirit, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I ſhall ſpeake, it may bee with ſuch trueth of his word, with ſuch zeale of his glory, with ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence of his Maieſty, as becometh his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, and this holy place. For <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> beeing<note place="margin">De <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> tion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> grat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 5.14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> Pe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> locis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> claſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> Zan <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>i, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> ſo high a point, wherein offence may bee giuen by wading too farre: by Gods aſſiſtance, it ſhall bee touched ſo plainely, and with ſuch moderation, as euer-more, I will be ſure to keepe the rule of the ſacred word of God, for my guide.</p>
                     <p>The purpoſe and drift of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in this place, is to proue vnto the <hi>Romans,</hi> beeing then in perſecution, that howſoeuer in this life, miſery and afflictions did befall them, yet their ſaluation
<pb facs="tcp:180996:5"/>
ſtood ſure and moſt certaine, becauſe it depended vpon the vnfallible purpoſe of GOD, which here is called <hi>Predeſtination.</hi> So that, <hi>Predeſtination</hi> is the ſecret and immutable purpoſe of God: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he hath decreed from all eternity, to call thoſe whom hee hath loued in his Sonne Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and through faith and good workes, to make them veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of eternall glory.</p>
                     <p>That God of his free mercie, hath made choyſe of ſome to eternall life, it is apparent in diuers places. <hi>Epheſians</hi> 1. and the 5. ver. <hi>Hee hath Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>vs, to bee adopted vnto himſelfe, through Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: according to the good pleaſure of his owne will.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the 2. to <hi>Timo.</hi> 1. the 8. and 9. verſ. <hi>Hee hath</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>. 1. 8</note> 
                        <hi>ſaued, vs, and called vs, according to his owne purpoſe and grace, which was giuen to vs, through Chriſt Ieſus, before the world was.</hi> So then, as the Potter<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> hath power ouer the clay, to make it, either a veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of honour, or diſhonour: ſo God hath power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſonnes of men: &amp; of his owne free mercy, hath made choyſe of ſome to eternall life, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hath left vnto perdition. <hi>God hath created al for himſelfe: and the wicked for the euill day.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 6.4.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now, if it be demaunded, why God hath made choiſe of ſome, and not of others, and ſo thought iniuſtice and want of compaſſion; that hee ſhould reiect men, before they bee borne, and brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the light: and ere euer they haue done good
<pb facs="tcp:180996:5"/>
or euill, as it is ſaid in the 9. to the <hi>Rom.</hi> the 11. and 12. ver. <hi>Yer euer the children were borne, when</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>they had done neither good nor euill (that the purpoſe of God might remaine, according to election) I haue lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Iacob, &amp; I haue hated Eſau:</hi> In this caſe, I firſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer plainely with the <hi>Prophet Iſaiah.</hi> in his 45.<note place="margin">Eſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> Chap. the 9. ver. <hi>Wo bee vnto him, that ſtriueth with his maker: or, what art thou (O man that dareſt ſtand vp<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to plead againſt God? The clay may not diſpute with the Potter.</hi> Man that is but duſt and aſhes, hee may not reaſon the caſe with his Creator. To knowe further, why God hath made choiſe of ſome and not of others: there is no other reaſon to be giuen, no other anſwer to be made, but that it is his good pleaſure, it is his will. <hi>Miſericordia eius, cauſa Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricordiae<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God ſheweth mercy, to whom he wil ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>and he hath compaſſion vpon whom it pleaſeth him to haue compaſſion.</hi> There is power and free liberty in<note place="margin">Exo. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> GOD, to giue and beſtowe his grace: both to whom, when, and how much-ſoeuer it pleaſeth him. <hi>Huic fit miſericordia, tibi non fit iuiuria</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) God chooſeth one, he refuſeth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: to him, he ſheweth mercy, to thee hee doth no iniury.</p>
                     <p>Here then wee muſt reſt: here we muſt make<note place="margin">Fat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> nece <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> em: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> uide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> ad ſa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> am: ſc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> a full point. It is Gods good pleaſure, it is his will. And this one anſwer, it is a barre for all deepe queſtions, either of <hi>of Predeſtination, Election, Deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> or any ſuch like. Iris Gods good pleaſure: it
<pb facs="tcp:180996:6"/>
is his will. His will is the cauſe of all cauſes: and<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> further we cannot go. Whom this anſwer doth not content, S. <hi>Gregory</hi> doth anſwer directly, <hi>Qui in factis Dei rationem non videt, infirmitatem ſuam conſiderans, cur non videat, rationem videt,</hi> In<note place="margin">Mag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> the hidden works of God, hee that ſeeth not a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, if he ſee his owne infirmity, hee ſeeth a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent reaſon, why he ſhould not ſee. Wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude then with good Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> in his 59. Epiſtle <hi>ad Paulinum; occulta eſſe cauſa poteſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſta</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> m.</note> 
                        <hi>eſſe non poteſt.</hi> Why God hath made choiſe of ſome, and not of others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> howſoeuer vnto vs the cauſe be hidden; yet vndoubtedly it cannot bee vniuſt.</p>
                     <p>This Doctrine briefely ſet downe, and thus plainely appearing: that <hi>Predeſtination is the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable purpoſe of God: whereby hee hath made choyſe of ſome, and reiected others, according to the pleaſure of his owne will:</hi> It ſeemeth at the firſt, when men do commit ſinne, they cannot auoide it, as if GOD had ſo ordained it. Hee hath made choyſe of ſome to life, and others hee hath reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: therefore when they ſinne, and follow the courſe that leadeth vnto death; they doe it of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity.<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 15.</note> 
                        <hi>O, God forbid, there ſhould bee vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse in God, or iniquity in the Almighty. For GOD hath commannded no man to doe vngodly: nether hath he giuen any man licence to ſinne.</hi> Before wee reſolue this doubt, there ariſeth a very notable
<pb facs="tcp:180996:6"/>
and neceſſary queſtion, which (in times paſt) hath troubled many wits. If God bee not the author of ſinne, if he bee not the cauſe of mans offending: how came ſinne firſt to be? how came it in? where was the firſt beginning of it? The heathen <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> they roued at the matter a farre off. The <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picures,</hi> they ſaid it came by chance. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and his ſect, they ſaid, it was the error of nature<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>Plato</hi> came a little nearer, and he ſaid, it aroſe <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> out of the nature of man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>Manicheus</hi> the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticke (to auoide the former opinions) hee fained two Gods. <hi>Duos affirmanit eſſe Deos; alterum qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> lib. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> cog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>bonum, alterum verò malum.</hi> One he auerred to be the author and firſt beginner of all good: the other the firſt cauſe and author of all euill.</p>
                     <p>This opinion went currant a long time, almoſt three hundred yeares, as <hi>Nicephorus</hi> writeth, and<note place="margin">Nic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> the reaſon was, becauſe, men neuer looking into the word of trueth; by the light of nature, they could neuer finde from whence ſinne came.</p>
                     <p>That we may fully vnderſtand this point: very briefely, we will ſet downe the lineall diſcent of ſinne.</p>
                     <p>Sinne firſt ariſeth from concupiſcence. <hi>Euery</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>man is tempted, when he is drawne away, by his owne concupiſcence, and is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ticed.</hi> All ſin, all wickednes of this life (whatſoeuer) firſt ariſeth from concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence, from our owne wicked inclination. From whence then comes concupiſcence? <hi>That Dauid</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:7"/>
ſhewes: <hi>ex immundo ſemine, We are borne in iniquiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, and we are conceiued in ſinne:</hi> as the originall doth<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> ſignifie, we are all warmed in vncleane bloud. If we be all borne in ſin, and by nature corrupt, wee muſt aſcend higher to our firſt parents; and know how they came firſt to ſinne. <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e</hi> (as appeareth in the 2. of <hi>Geneſ.</hi> they firſt ſinned, by yeelding conſent vnto the Deuill: they tooke it from Sathan. Heere then comes in the maine queſtion, how came the Deuill firſt to ſinne? The Deuill at firſt was created <hi>in poreſtate ſtandi &amp; ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendi:</hi> he had in his firſt creation, a poſſibility, to ſtand or fall: power of continuance: that hee had from God: poſſibility of falling: that he had from himſelfe. For it is a ground in diuinity. <hi>Immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliter bonum eſſe, Dei propriumeſt.</hi> To bee immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie good, without any change or alteration, it is onely proper vnto God: therefore, had hee poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility to ſtand or to fall. <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> alſo, he ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth another reaſon, why the Deuill (created an Angell of light) had poſſibility of falling. Becauſe (ſaith he) at the firſt, hee was created of nothing, therefore he had in him poſſibility to retutne to nothing, if ſo be, he did not rely in the goodneſſe of his creator, if he did not ſubiect himſelfe vnder the power of God.</p>
                     <p>To reſolue then: Sathan at the firſt was created an angell of light, and had poſſibilitie to ſtand or fall: but in the 14. of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and the 14. ver. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb facs="tcp:180996:7"/>
he ſaith there: <hi>I wil a ſcend aboue the height of the cloudes: I will be like the moſt high.</hi> Then did Sathan chooſe rather, to be an abſolute nature in himſelfe, to ſhake of his alleageance, and to abandon the goodneſſe of God: then (relying ſtill in God) to be eſtabliſhed by his power. Our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith; <hi>I ſaw Sathan fall as lightning from heauen.</hi> And<note place="margin">L <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> the lightning we know, is not caſt downe by any other: but it falleth, and breaketh out of it ſelfe alone. <hi>The Diuell (ſaith</hi> S. Peter) <hi>was caſt downe to</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2. P <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>hell, and deliuered vnto chaines of darkenes.</hi> The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is rendred in the 6. of <hi>Iude:</hi> becauſe when hee had poſſibilitie to ſtand or fall, hee kept not his firſt eſtate. <hi>Non perſtitit in veritate: Iohn</hi> the 8. 44. <hi>He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boad not in the trueth.</hi> So then, to deſcend againe. The Diuell, he is <hi>Primitiuus pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>cator,</hi> hee was the firſt offender: <hi>For he ſinneth from the beginning.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. Io <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> From the deuill ſinne was deriued vnto <hi>Adam:</hi> from <hi>Adam,</hi> to all his poſterity, borne of vncleane ſeede fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the corruption of vncleane birth, it is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueighed to our inclination, to concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. Thus from the Diuell, ſinne firſt boyleth vp; as out of a maine Sea: from him, when it comes to <hi>Adam,</hi> it ariſeth, as out off a ſpring: from this ſpring, it is reſerued in nature, as in a Conduit: from nature, conua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed to concupiſcence; as hy a pipe: &amp; from thence, doth iſſue a ſtreame of wickedneſſe, to the Sea againe.</p>
                     <p>Now: although it be thus manifeſt, that ſinne
<pb facs="tcp:180996:8"/>
doth proceede from the ſuggeſtion of Sathan working with our owne concupiſcence: yet, euill and godleſſe men, they thinke they are tempted of God: and when they ſinne, they do not ſticke to ſay, <hi>God hath ſo decreed it, let him therefore worke his will: for who hath euer reſiſted his will. Homer</hi> that notable Heathen Poet, hee anſwered ſuch men very fitly, in the perſon of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> ſpeaking in this ſort.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <note place="margin">Od. 2.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>O yee fooliſh mortall men, euer and anone, you cry out of the immortall Gods, imputing to them the cauſe of yous miſeries, when (indeede) your ſelues are the workers of your owne wo.<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 4. 2.</note> 
                        <hi>Perditio tua ex te, O Iſrael, Thou haſt fallen by thine owne iniquity. Stigias vltrò quaerimus vndas.</hi> Like the <hi>Oſtridge,</hi> we do pricke our ſelues with our own feathers; and we our ſelues do cauſe the ſhippe to leake, where we ſaile. <hi>Onely (lo) this haue I found that God hath made man righteous, but they haue ſought out many inuentions. Quare peccas, quiane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcis?</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>. 31.</note> 
                        <hi>&amp;c.</hi> How comes it to paſſe, ſaith S. <hi>Aug.</hi> that thou doſt ſinne: becauſe thou art ignorant? it is not ſo. Why doſt thou ſin? becauſe thou art com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled? there is no ſuch matter: why doeſt thou ſinne? becauſe it pleaſeth, it delighteth thy wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and corrupted nature. <hi>In the tranſgreſsion of a</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 9. 5.</note>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:8"/>
                        <hi>man, is his ſn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>re.</hi> Of our owne accord, wee runne wilfully into the dead fall of ſinne: ſo is it in the 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> and 16. verſ. <hi>The vngodly is trapped, how? not by God, but by the workes of his owne hands.</hi> The Lord our God is good, holy and onely holy: ſo holy, that (as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith) the <hi>Angels are vncleane in his ſight:</hi> ſo pure, that his Miniſters, the <hi>Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> are of fire moſt cleere: and yet, the <hi>Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins</hi> and <hi>Seraphins</hi> do couer their faces with their wings, as not able to behold the perfect brightnes of his moſt pure and vndefiled Maieſtie. Therfore, although no action can be done without God, and that his power is ſo in all things, that we cannot ſo much, as lift vp our fingar without him. <hi>For in him we liue, and moue, and haue all our being:</hi> Yet is not God the cauſe of any ſin: <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.<note place="margin">Act. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> Wee cannot faſten the leaſt touch of any euill vppon GOD. But ſo it ſtands. <hi>Vna eademque actio tribuitur &amp; cauſae principali, &amp; inſtrumentali.</hi> In one and the ſelfe ſame action, there is a double cauſe. Firſt, the inſtrumentall cauſe mouing: then God ſeparated from the inſtrument; yet giuing power of motion to the ſame. Through this dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cauſe of moouing, there is a double worke, which vnto vs ſeemeth to be but one. For exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: God (as appeareth in the 2. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> and the 23. ver.) by his determinate counſell and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, deliuered vp our Sauiour Chriſt, as the principall cauſe; <hi>Iudas</hi> as the inſtrumentall
<pb facs="tcp:180996:9"/>
cauſe: yet, neither is God to bee drawne in, as a party in <hi>Iudas</hi> fault; nor <hi>Iudas</hi> to bee excuſed as furthering the worke of God: For God neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Iudas</hi> to deliuer vp Chriſt: nor <hi>Iudas</hi> in deliuering him had any ſuch intention, as to doe God ſeruice in the execution of his will. <hi>Deus agit per malos, non in malis.</hi> The wicked are the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God: Yet not God the cauſe of their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. God is the cauſe of the action, but not of the euill, or quality in the action. For example: A man trauaileth his horſe by the way, he is the cauſe of his going: but, if his horſe halts or haue an ill pace, he is not the cauſe of his ill going.</p>
                     <p>A cunning man ſtriketh an inſtrument with his fingars; he is the cauſe of the ſound, but if the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument be bad, or the ſtrings not well choſen, hee is not the cauſe of the ill ſound.</p>
                     <p>The Iron ruſteth: thou wilt not wite it vpon the Smith. Wine ſowreth, the fault is not in the vint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. In the heauens, there is a double motion <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>: The fixed Starres, and the whole<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> Globe of all, is carried about with one Sphere, and with one motion: yet the planets in themſelues, haue a wandring and vncertaine courſe. The like,<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> we may vſually behold in euery clocke, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and higheſt wheele moueth, and carryeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout all the reſt, yet in this motion, ſome wheeles turne to the right hand, others to the left, and that by a contrary courſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:9"/>So then it fareth thus with the wicked. As hee that hath an euill and corrupt ſtomacke, if hee doe eate hony, it turneth into gall: or, as if a mans hand be out of ioynt, when he would moue it one way, it turnes another: ſo the wicked and godleſſe men, whereas the light of nature, Gods ſpirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and his word leadeth them one way, their owne vil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> inclination, their own concupiſcence leadeth them another.</p>
                     <p>Now then, what ſhall we ſay? is there vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe with God? doth he cauſe vs to commit ſinne? No, God forbid, <hi>wickedneſſe ſhould bee in God, or iniquity in the Almighty.</hi> But as it is ſaide before. <hi>Euery man is drawne away by his owne concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iob. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>and is inticed: luſt, when it hath conceiued, bringeth forth ſin: and ſinne, when it is finiſhed, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>forth death.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hauing hitherto freed God from all imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of euil, by ſhewing from whence ſin comes, and that God is not the author of it, wee doe heere meete with the <hi>Pelagian Heretike</hi> (who not able to vntie this knot) affirmes that the wicked are reiected, for the ſins which God fore-ſaw they would commit: and ſo contrariwiſe, the godly, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting the grace of God by their merits, are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinated, and choſen through faith, and good workes, which GOD fore-ſaw, they ſhould doe: Making Gods eternall election to depend vppon our faith, and vppon our workes; whereas (cleane
<pb facs="tcp:180996:10"/>
contrary) our faith, our good workes, and all the good that is in vs, doth wholy depend vppon Gods free election.</p>
                     <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith directly. <hi>God hath choſen vs in</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>his ſonne Chriſt, before the foundation of the world was.</hi> If in Chriſt? Aſſuredly it appeares, we were vnworthy in our ſelues, and ſo Gods election is the cauſe of our good workes. <hi>Et cauſa non eſt poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior ſuo effectu,</hi> the cauſe, it doth neuer follow the effect.</p>
                     <p>The learned Schooleman, makes it plaine: <hi>Non ideo electus eſt quis, quia talis futurus erat, ſed ex ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Lomb<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>electione talis eſt factus:</hi> No man was euer cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen through faith and good workes, which GOD fore-ſaw that hee ſhould doe: but the faith and good workes, which we now doe, proceede from the eternall election, which went before.</p>
                     <p>This doth the Apoſtle very plainely ſet downe.<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m. 1. 9</note> 
                        <hi>God hath ſaued vs, and called vs, not according to our workes, but according to his owne purpoſe and grace, which was giuen to vs, through</hi> Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>before the world was.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:180996:10"/>
                     <head>Calling.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>Moreouer whom he Predeſtinated, them alſo he Called.</p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S from the maine Sea, we do ſtrike into ſome chanell or riuer: So fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>Predeſtination</hi> (the great depth of Gods Councel) the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto <hi>Calling.</hi> For, whereas it hath beene ſhewedin opening the firſt point, that God of his free mercy did chooſe ſome to life: and others hath left vnto Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. In this caſe, if God ſhould neuer <hi>Call</hi> men, if he ſhould neuer offer them grace, it might ſeeme preiudiciall to his mercy; and though wee did ſinne, yet it might be thought, our ſelues could not redreſſe it. For this cauſe the Apoſtle commeth from <hi>Predeſtination</hi> to <hi>Calling:</hi> that is, from Gods determinate counſell, to the meanes, which hee hath appointed for our ſaluation.</p>
                     <p>This <hi>Calling</hi> is two-fold, eyther outward, or inward. The outward and generall <hi>Calling,</hi> is, by the workes of God, and by his word. Firſt, by his
<pb facs="tcp:180996:11"/>
workes. This world, it is an <hi>Vniuerſity,</hi> or a <hi>Colledge:</hi> wherein there are two <hi>Lectures,</hi> whereof euery man liuing muſt bee an hearer, and a learner. The firſt, is the <hi>Philoſophy</hi> lecture, concerning Gods<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> workes, in the heauens, and all his creatures: by the which we are taught, and daylie <hi>Called</hi> to know God.</p>
                     <p>This, is a plaine, and eaſie Lecture, written in great<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>Capitall</hi> Letters, that euery ſimple, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant man may read it running. The other is the <hi>Diuinitie Lecture,</hi> when we are exempted from the firſt, and led on further to know God in his word. Both theſe <hi>Lectures;</hi> they are expreſſed together<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> in the 19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> From the 1. verſ. to the 7. is contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the <hi>Philoſophie</hi> Lecture. <hi>The Heauens declare</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 9. 1.</note> 
                        <hi>the glory of God: and the Firmament ſheweth his handie worke. Day vnto day vttereth the ſame, and Night vnto night teacheth knowledge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there is no</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>ſpeech <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>or language, where their voyce is not heard. Their ſound is gone forth through all the earth, and their words vnto the ends of the world. In them, hath hee ſet a Tabernacle for the Sunne, which commeth forth as a Bridegroome out of his Chamber; and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth like a mighty man, to run his race: His going out is from the end of the heauen: and his compaſſe is vnto the ends of the ſame, and none is hid from the heate thereof.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Diuinity Lecture begins at the ſeauenth verſe, and continues to the 11. verſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:11"/>
                        <hi>The law of the Lord; is an vndefiled Law, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting the ſoule: the teſtimony of the Lord is ſure: and giueth wiſedome to the ſimple. The Statutes of the Lord are right: and reioyce the heart. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of the Lord is pure: and giueth light vnto the eyes. The feare of the Lord is cleane: and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth for euer. The iudgements of the Lord are true and righteous altogether. More to bee deſired then gold: yea, then much fine gold: ſweeter alſo then hony, and the honye combe: Moreouer by them, is thy ſeruant taught, and in keeping of them there is great reward.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Touching the Philoſophy Lecture: that we are all firſt <hi>Called,</hi> to know God by his workes; it is moſt apparent. For <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>eſt Diuinitatis ſymbolum:</hi> the world is the glaſſe of Gods Diuinity. The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then<note place="margin">I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> De <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> riis.</note> Philoſopher ſaith: <hi>Deus tangitur in operibus.</hi> God is euen touched in his workes. He iumpeth with S. <hi>Paul. Acts</hi> 17. 27. <hi>The heathen by groping</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Act. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>might haue found him. for doubtleſſe, he is not farre from euery one of vs.</hi> In the 143. Pſalme, and the 5.<note place="margin">Pſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> verſe, the holy Prophet ſaith thus. <hi>I will muſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon all thy workes and exerciſe my ſelfe in the workes of thy hands.</hi> If a man will profi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> by this philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy lecture, he muſt vſe meditation. For indeede, if a man doe rightly conſider of the Ebbing, and Flowing of the Sea, where of no reaſon can be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. of the certaine courſe, and change <hi>of the Moone, with the ſecret influence of the ſame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:12"/>
                        <hi>of winde,</hi> no man knowing, whence it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, nor whether it goeth: the hugeneſſe of the ſweeling Sea, girt by Gods commaundement, that it doth not ouerflow the banckes: the raging<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> Thunder, which makes al the beaſts of the field to tremble: the fearfull Lightning; which in the twinckling of an eye, paſſeth from <hi>Eaſt</hi> to <hi>Weſt;</hi> how all things keepe their appointed courſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they were created. As wee walke abroad in the fields, if wee doe behold, and view the glory of the <hi>Sunne,</hi> and <hi>Moone:</hi> the beauty of the <hi>Starres:</hi> the ſweet <hi>Dew:</hi> diſtilling <hi>Showers:</hi> greene <hi>Paſtures;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> pleaſant <hi>Meddowes;</hi> cleare <hi>Springs;</hi> thicke <hi>Woodes,</hi> guſhing <hi>Fountaines:</hi> the wonderfull increaſe of <hi>Corne, Cattle,</hi> and ſuch like: Who is hee (behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe things, and ſeriouſly meditating vpon this Philoſophy lecture) but hee muſt needes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that God doth <hi>Call</hi> him, being ſo manifeſtly<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> taught to know him in his workes?</p>
                     <p>And, as God is thus ſeene, and taught vnto all the heathen people by his workes, in <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> in the frame and compoſition of this great world, ſo likewiſe GOD doth <hi>Call</hi> vs, by his workes in <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> in the little World of man. <hi>Homo eſt cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li ſimulachrum, &amp; interpres naturae.</hi> Man, he is the picture of the Heauens, and the interpreter of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Concerning God, we acknowledge him to be a ſpirit; concerning the World, we haue found it to be a body: in <hi>Man,</hi> we haue an abridgement
<pb facs="tcp:180996:12"/>
of both, namely, of <hi>God,</hi> in regard of his ſpirit; of the <hi>World,</hi> in the compoſition of the body; as though the <hi>Creator</hi> (vpon purpoſe, to ſet forth a mirror of his workes) intended to bring into this one little compaſſe of man, both the infiniteneſſe of his owne nature, and the hugeneſſe of the whole <hi>world</hi> together.</p>
                     <p>As in the <hi>World,</hi> ſo in the body of man, there is a wonderfull mixture of the foure <hi>Elements.</hi> The <hi>Heart,</hi> placed in the mideſt, as the <hi>Earth</hi> our cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre: the <hi>Liuer,</hi> like the <hi>Sea,</hi> from whence the liuely ſprings of bloud doe flow: the <hi>Veines</hi> (like riuers) ſpredding themſelues abroad vnto the vttermoſt members: the <hi>Braine,</hi> which giueth light and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, placed aloft like the Sunne: the <hi>Senſes</hi> ſet round about, like ſtarres for ornament: the <hi>Countenance</hi> of man, full of grace, and Maieſty, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a terror into all Creatures. Such and ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull is God in his power, that he is ſeene in the workemanſhip of the body.</p>
                     <p>But if man (as it were out of himſelfe) could behold this body, receiuing life, and entring into the vſe of all his motions: <hi>Ioints,</hi> mouing ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely: <hi>Sinewes,</hi> ſtirring ſo nimbly; <hi>Senſes,</hi> vttering their force ſo ſharpely: The <hi>inward Powers,</hi> ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent: the <hi>Spirit,</hi> ſupernaturall: <hi>Reaſon,</hi> ſo Diuine: the <hi>Minde</hi> &amp; <hi>Cogitation,</hi> ſo quicke and infinite: the <hi>Vnderſtanding,</hi> ſo Angel-like: and the <hi>Soule</hi> (aboue all) <hi>Dei</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> the ingrauen image of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall
<pb facs="tcp:180996:13"/>
God. If man could enter into himſelfe, and conſider rightly of this, he muſt needes bee driuen to confeſſe, that God hath <hi>Called</hi> him, by thoſe workes, which are moſt apparent in himſelfe.<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Therefore as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſoundly reaſoneth, in the 1. to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and the 20. verſ. No man can excuſe himſelfe. Neither the <hi>Turkes,</hi> who acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>Mahomet</hi> their great prophet: nor the <hi>Indians,</hi> that worſhip the Sunne. nor the, <hi>Egiptians,</hi> who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſacrifice to all manner of beaſts: neyther they, or any other remote, and barbarous people, that<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> do worſhip ſtrange Idols of their owne inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: none of theſe can excuſe himſelfe, and ſay he is not <hi>Called: becauſe the inuiſible things of GOD (his eternall power and Godhead) are ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ene by the creation of the world, being conſidered in his workes: to the intent, all men might be without excuſe.</hi> Thus<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> we ſee, by this <hi>Philoſophy</hi> lecture, all people (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer) are inſtructed to know God. But to his own people, God reades Diuinity Lecture: hee <hi>Calleth</hi> and teacheth them by his word. In the 146. Pſal. and the two laſt verſes. <hi>GOD hath giuen his word</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>vnto Iacob, his ſtatutes, and his ordinances vnto Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell. Hee hath not dealt ſo with euery Nation, neither haue the heathen knowledge of his Lawes.</hi> So then, as in the 1. of <hi>King.</hi> 6. 28 verſe, there is mention made of three <hi>Courts</hi> of the <hi>Temple</hi> at <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> wherein God was worſhipped: ſo here are three Courts.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:13"/>Firſt, we behold God in the frame, and compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the <hi>Heauen,</hi> and the <hi>Earth,</hi> as the great and outtermoſt <hi>Court:</hi> then we ſee <hi>God</hi> in our ſelues, in the workemanſhippe of the body, in the powers of the minde, and ſoule: there is the inner <hi>Court.</hi> Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with the high prieſt, wee enter into <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum;</hi> that is, wee behold God, and learne to know him, in his ſacred and heauenly Word. All the Prophets, &amp; Apoſtles, all the Miniſters of God, they are <hi>Diuinity Lecturers:</hi> and all Nations, peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and kinred, to whom they haue, &amp; do preach the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt; all theſe haue their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Calling:</hi> and vnto all theſe, grace mercie, and ſaluation in Chriſt Ieſus, hath beene offered. And hereof is that place vnderſtood in the 20. of <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. verſ, <hi>Many are Called, but few are choſen</hi> (i) by the outward <hi>Calling,</hi> both of the workes of God, &amp; of his word, many are <hi>Called</hi> (for this outward <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> is common both to good and bad) but by the inward <hi>Calling,</hi> effectually working in them a liuely faith, apprehending Chriſt: ſo, very few are <hi>Called.</hi> Here in this place of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> is ment a more ſpeciall, powerfull, and inward <hi>Calling,</hi> which is wrought by Gods ſpirit; and ioyned with faith: ſo doth Saint <hi>Auguſt.</hi> expound it, in his booke <hi>de Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinatione ſanctorum. Non quacunque, ſed qua vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catione fit credens.</hi> Whomſoeuer God hath choſen to life, him hee hath alſo <hi>Called</hi> by that <hi>Calling,</hi> whereby hee is made, and becomes faithfull. <hi>Acts</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:14"/>
the 16. and 14. <hi>A certaine woman named Lidia heard vs.</hi> There is the outward <hi>Calling: and the Lord ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 14. 13.</note> 
                        <hi>her heart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhe attended to the things, which</hi> Paul <hi>ſpake, and ſhe was baptiſed.</hi> there is the inward <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> This then is the ſound, and plaine meaning of theſe words: <hi>Wbom he hath predeſtinated, thoſe hee hath called;</hi> that is, thoſe whom hee hath choſen to eternall life, hee hath alſo ordained to vſe the meanes of ſaluation, which is an effectuall <hi>Calling by his word and ſpirit.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hauing diſcuſſed this ſecond point whereby it appeareth, how all men liuing are <hi>Called,</hi> both by<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> the workes of God, and by his word, we may here ſee, how the diſſolute liuers, and prophane <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts</hi> of theſe our times deceiue themſelues. It is a common conceit foſtred in the boſome of many; yea; vile and ſenſuall men, they will not ſticke to ſay: <hi>If I be ſaued, I am ſaued: If I be choſen to life, I</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>am ſure of ſaluation: If otherwiſe, I cannot auoide it.</hi> Aſſuredly, ſuch men, they doe ſpeake as peruerſly, and as ſenſeleſſely, as if a man ſhould ſay, that hee would gladly be at <hi>Yorke,</hi> and yet will vſe neither horſe, foote, nor Wagon, but will flie thither. For the determinate counſell of God, it doth not take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the nature and property of ſecondary cauſes, it doth not take away the meanes of ſaluation: but rather, Gods ſecret counſell, it doth ſet thoſe cauſes in order, and doth diſpoſe of thoſe meanes to their appointed end.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:14"/>Gods purpoſe, his eternall decree is not to be ſought out in his botomeleſſe counſell. For then<note place="margin">Ro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 33.</note> we muſt all cry out with Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>O the deepeneſſe of the riches, both of the wiſdome and knowledge of God: how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable are his iudgements? and his waies paſt fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But, Gods purpoſe, his eternall decree is to bee ſought out in the meanes, and in the manifeſtation, appointed for the ſame.</p>
                     <p>The courſe and order of mans Saluation, is like a <hi>Golden Chaine;</hi> And this verſe may fitly bee called <hi>Iacobs Ladder,</hi> whereupon the Angells and Saints of the Church, doe diſcend, and aſcend vnto God. <hi>Iacob</hi> wreſtled with the <hi>Angel,</hi> at the foote of the <hi>Ladder:</hi> wee muſt not bee ſo hardye as to wreſtle with God at the top of the <hi>Ladder.</hi> Wee ſee here, God hath ſet downe, not onely <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination,</hi> as though wee ſhould ſtay there: but <hi>Iuſtification</hi> and <hi>Calling,</hi> as middle ſteppes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, whereby we muſt aſcend vnto God. Wee muſt not pull downe the Ladder, and thinke to iumpe into heauen. To ſay, <hi>If I be ſaued, I am ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued;</hi> it is the Diuells Diuinity. When our Sauiour was vpon the Pinacle, hee bad him caſt himſelfe downe headlong, for (ſaith hee) <hi>God hath giuen his</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Angels charge ouer thee, leaſt at any time, thou daſh thy foote againſt a ſtone.</hi> He left out the chiefe point (in all his wayes) it was not the right way from the
<pb facs="tcp:180996:15"/>
pinnacle, to caſt himſelfe downe headlong.</p>
                     <p>No more is it here the way, to ſtand vppon this high point and dangerous pinnacle of <hi>Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> to caſt a mans ſelfe downe headlong, deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, ſaying: <hi>If I bee ſaued, I am ſaued.</hi> In the 2. of<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 11.</note> 
                        <hi>Oze.</hi> 11. ver. the Lord there promiſing temporall bleſſings, ſetteth downe an order &amp; a courſe, howe they hang togither. I (ſaith the Lord) <hi>will heare the Heauens, and the heauens ſhall heare the Earth, and the earth ſhall heare the Corne, and wine and Oyle, and the Corne &amp; VVine &amp; oyle ſhall heare</hi> Iſraell. So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, in the ſpirituall bleſſing of the Soule, there are<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> meanes, &amp; an order, how we come vnto the ſame: God by his ſonne Chriſt, Chriſt by his Word: his Word worketh by his Spirit: his Spirit doth certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our hearts: our hearts ſtand faſt by faith: Faith catcheth hold vppon Chriſt: and ſo backe againe, Chriſt preſenteth vs vnto God.</p>
                     <p>Heere likewiſe in this Scripture: God hath <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen</hi> vs from euerlaſting; there is <hi>Predeſtination;</hi> he doth not there leaue vs, but then he doth teach vs by his word; there is <hi>Calling:</hi> this word (through his ſpirit) engendreth faith; there is <hi>Iuſtifiyng:</hi> this <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying</hi> faith lifts vs vp vnto God, there is <hi>Glorifiyng.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Common ſenſe and reaſon doth teach vs. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. In euery action, the end &amp;<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>h. P. 7.</note> the meanes of the end, muſt go together. The ende which euery one of vs doth deſire, and ayme at, it is eternall glory: we muſt be ſure then to lay hold
<pb facs="tcp:180996:15"/>
vpon <hi>Calling</hi> and <hi>Iuſtifiyng,</hi> as the meanes ordained to come vnto this end. For this is a certaine and ſure ground in diuinity, and Religion: Whom-ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer God hath appointed to eternall life, he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo appointed that man to vſe the meanes whereby he may come vnto the ſame.</p>
                     <p>To make this more plaine, let it pleaſe you to vouch ſafe the hearing of an accident, which fell out, very fitly to this purpoſe.</p>
                     <p>One <hi>Ludouicus</hi> a learned man of <hi>Italy,</hi> yet wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the direction of Gods good ſpirit, and ſo neuer conſidering aduiſedly, of the meanes of our Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; he grew at laſt to this reſolution. <hi>Si ſaluabor, ſaluabor.</hi> It bootes not what I doe, nor how I liue: <hi>For if I bee ſaued, I am ſaued.</hi> Thus <hi>Ludouicus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched with this deſperate opinion, continued a long time: till at length hee grew very dangerouſly ſicke: wherevpon he ſent for a cunning and learned Phiſition, and earneſtly requeſted his helpe. The Phiſition before-hand made acquainted with his former lewd aſſertion, how in his health hee would vſually ſay, <hi>If I bee ſaued, I am ſaued:</hi> he likewiſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected his ſpeech to the ſame purpoſe, and ſaid: Sure it ſhall bee needleſſe to vſe any meanes for your recouery, neither doe I purpoſe to miniſter vnto you: for, if the time of your death bee not come, you haue no cauſe to feare, you ſhall liue; and do well inough without Phiſicke: and if the time of your death bee nowe come, it is vnpoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:180996:16"/>
to auoide it. <hi>Ludouicus,</hi> muſing in his bed of the matter, and conſidering aduiſedly of the phiſitions ſpeech: finding by reaſon, that as meanes were to be vſed, for the health of the body: ſo God alſo had<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> ordained meanes for the ſaluation of the Soule, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on further conference (with ſhame &amp; griefe) he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canted his former opinion, tooke phiſicke, and ſo was happily cured both of ſoule and body at one time.</p>
                     <p>By this doctrine of Gods loue ſo manifeſtly <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> vs: we directly learne, that if a man doe thirſt after his ſaluation: if a man would bee throughly<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> aſſured in his heart and conſcience, that God hath choſen him to eternall life, hee muſt not ruſh pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently into <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> into Gods ſecret Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell: but he muſt enter into himſelfe to trie, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, whether hee bee rightly <hi>Called:</hi> for as the ſureſt way to come vnto the ſea, is firſt to finde out<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> a riuer: ſo concerning our ſaluation, the plaineſt &amp; ſureſt way, to finde out the depth of Gods coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, is firſt to come vnto <hi>Calling,</hi> vnto <hi>Iuſtifying</hi> which are as ſweet and liuely ſprings flowing from the ſame.</p>
                     <p>We know, and ſee dayly by experience, wee are not able to diſcerne, wee cannot pierce with the eye, to ſee what matter the Sunne is of: but we can plainely ſee, and manifeſtly perceiue, both beames, and heat, and light proceeding from the ſame. So heere (concerning the firſt point of <hi>Predeſtination</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:16"/>
alone) wee cannot conceiue it, wee are not able to pierce it, for it is the way, which the Eagles eye hath not ſeene: but <hi>Calling</hi> and <hi>Iuſtifying,</hi> which are as heate and light proceeding from the ſame: thoſe we may as comfortably perceiue, as wee doe ſenſibly feele the heate and operation of the Sun. Here then is the duty of a true Chriſtian, heere is the part of a religious and good man indeede, not to venter his ſaluation vpon a bare ſpeech, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of <hi>Predeſtination:</hi> but to vſe all meanes poſſible which God hath ordained.</p>
                     <p>That he may truely be <hi>Called,</hi> to heare the word of God, and to ioy in hearing of it, with loue, and with a deſire to profit, that hee may bee <hi>Iuſtifyed,</hi> (when he hath heard) to be feruent in prayer, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of well doing, and abundant in all good works of Charity: that he may be <hi>Glorified</hi> in the life to come, to conſecrate both ſoule and body, and all the whole courſe of his life vnto God, that ſo grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp from faith to faith, from vertue to vertue, from hearing to beleeuing, from <hi>Calling</hi> to <hi>Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> at length, Gods ſpirit may ſatiſfie our ſpirits, that we are his, our bodies his, our ſoules his, &amp; wee ſetled, and ſealed vp in a Chriſtian ioy for euer.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore, I beſeech you all, by the mercies of God, and I intreate you, as you hope to ſtand with comfort before God and his Angels at the laſt day: euery man lay hold vppon his ſoule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times: do not eſteeme the loue of any thing in this
<pb facs="tcp:180996:17"/>
World, more then the loue of God, purchaſed in his ſonne Chriſt Ieſus. Take heede, and beware of this profane ſpeech: <hi>If I be ſaued, I am ſaued;</hi> vtter it not in word, thinke it not in heart, away with it:<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> For God is not the cauſe of our condemnation, it is our ſelues (Woe vnto vs wretches) we our ſelues are the workers of our owne deſtruction. <hi>Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> 1. 13. <hi>O ſeeke not Death in the error of the ſoule</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 13.</note> 
                        <hi>and deſtroy not your ſelues, with the workes of your owne hands. Bis interimitur, qui ſuis armis interimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> Euery man catch hold vpon this <hi>Chaine,</hi> worke and make ſure his ſaluation, and ſtriue to walke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> the Lord in trueth, &amp; with a perfect heart. On the one ſide, let no man paſſe on, in a ſecure and careleſſe courſe of life: nor on the other ſide, curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly prie into the hidden counſell of the Lord; but euery good Chriſtan, with an humble ſpirit, with an honeſt minde; with a cheerefull and good heart,<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> ſeeke to apprehend thoſe meanes which God hath appointed for his ſaluation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:180996:17"/>
                     <head>Iuſtification.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>The third <hi>Lincke</hi> of this <hi>Chaine</hi> is <hi>Iuſtification.</hi> Whom he hath <hi>Called,</hi> thoſe he hath <hi>Iuſtified.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a principle in reaſon. <hi>Actio perfect a non recipitur, niſi imperfectè primò:</hi> An habit is not gotten at the firſt, the work of our regeneration is not wrought on a ſodaine. But as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith: <hi>The Codly grow from ſtrength to ſtrength:</hi> and the wiſe<note place="margin">Pſal. 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> man ſheweth how: <hi>The light of the righteous ſhineth more and more, to the perfect day:</hi> So here, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pr. 56. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> (foote by foote) leadeth vs from one degree vnto another, till at length, we may come to make our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection ſure. This <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> it goeth a ſtep far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then <hi>Calling.</hi> For <hi>Calling,</hi> is an enlightning the mind with ſpiritual knowledge: <hi>Iuſtifying,</hi> an eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing the heart with a grounded perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> is the beginning of conuerſion, but <hi>Iuſtifying</hi> is a full clearing of the heart: <hi>Calling,</hi> is the firſt change of one that is regenerate, but <hi>Iuſtifying,</hi> is the full perſwaſion of the Soule, when the ſpirit of grace reſteth in vs, and we ſetled and truely ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in an holy chriſtian courſe of life.</p>
                     <p>So then, when we haue not onely ſorrowed for ſinnes paſt, which is the firſt ſtep of our <hi>Calling:</hi> but
<pb facs="tcp:180996:18"/>
further, when wee are renewed in ſpirit, and ſo changed in our life, that for the moſt part our thoughts, words, and workes, are guided by the good ſpirit of God, for (<hi>as many as are led by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> 8. 14</note> 
                        <hi>of God, thoſe are the ſonnes of God</hi>) then wee may aſſure our ſelues, that we are <hi>Iuſtifyed.</hi> How ſoeuer we be choſen from the beginning by Gods loue, and after <hi>Called</hi> by his word, yet there is neuer aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance vnto vs, vntill the Holy Ghoſt hath ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it vp in our hearts, which ſealing is our <hi>Iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus to aſſure vs of our <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to be <hi>Called</hi> to the knowledge of Saluation in Chriſt by his word; but after this knowledge, to lay hold vpon Chriſt by a working faith, and ſo to hold on, and continue ſtill, an holy, Chriſtian, and ſincere courſe of life, that at length, as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith: <hi>In water, face anſwereth face:</hi> ſo in this<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> 27. 19</note> worke of <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> our ſpirit may anſwer vnto Gods ſpirit, that we are his. Euen as the pure and Chriſtall Glaſſe, doth liuely repreſent the Image, which is ſet before it: ſo the heart once <hi>Iuſtifyed</hi> by a liucly faith in Chriſt, in ſome good meaſure doth expreſſe the image of God, and ſtriueth to come vnto this marke, which is here propounded, namely our <hi>Glorifycation.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:180996:18"/>
                     <head>Glorifying.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fourth <hi>Linke</hi> of this <hi>Cheine,</hi> is <hi>Glorifying.</hi> Which <hi>Glorifying,</hi> is the higheſt ſteppe of <hi>Salomons</hi> Throne: it is the exceeding great reward, which God promiſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> it is that eternal weight of glory, wherof, I neither know how to begin, nor how to make an end of ſpeaking. <hi>In vita aeterna, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliùs</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>poſſumus dicere, quid ibi non ſit, quàm quid ibi ſit.</hi> In deſcribing the glorie of the world to come, it is eaſier to expreſſe what is not there, then what is there. For there is no diſcontentment, nor griefe, no faintneſſe, nor infirmitie, no mourning, nor mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie, no corruption, nor, death: but ioy, &amp; fulnes of ioy for euer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſuch ioy, as if we had once taſted, wee would deſpiſe the pleaſures of a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d worlds, in hope of aſſurance to inioy it. For, after we haue wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded through the miſeries of this life, at length (in the twinckling of an eye, in a moment, with the ſound of a Trumpet) wee ſhall bee carried into the heauenly Paradiſe, into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſom: thouſand thouſands of <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue vs with ioy and ſinging: Our meate ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:180996:19"/>
bee that bread of life, and that Heauenly <hi>Manna</hi> which will taſt like whatſoeuer thing wee deſire: our drinke ſhall be the water of life; which, if we haue once taſted, we ſhall neuer thirſt again, our mirth and muſicke, ſhall be the ſong of the <hi>Saints Alleluia, honour and praiſe, and glory bee vnto him,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>. 13.</note> 
                        <hi>that ſitteth vpon the Throne, and vnto the Lambe for euermore.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There ſhall we reioyce continually in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the holy ONE, wee ſhall be his Saints, and he ſhall be our God: neither ſhall we feare death any more, neither ſorrow, nor crying, nor feele any want againe.</p>
                     <p>The Lord of Hoſtes, who is the King of glory he will take vs by the right hand, and leade vs to the garden of comfort, to the fountaine of ioy, where all our garments ſhall bee waſhed pure, in the blood of the Lambe, and allteares ſhall be waſhed from our eyes.</p>
                     <p>There ſhall we ſee the Courts of the Lord of Hoſts, new <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the Citty of the great king. Where there is no night, nor any candle, nor yet the light of the Sunne: for, the Lord himſelfe ſhal be our light, and with him, we ſhall ſhine as the ſtarre in Heauen.</p>
                     <p>Heere ſhall we bee clothed with white robes, the innocency of Saints; wee ſhall haue <hi>Palmes</hi> in our hands in token of victory. We ſhall be crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a diadem of pure gold, which is immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality:
<pb facs="tcp:180996:19"/>
and ſeruing God a while in this ſhort life, there ſhall we haue riches without meaſure; life, without death; liberty, without thraldome; ſolace without ceaſing; &amp; ioy without ending. O, bleſſed are they (Lord) that dwell in thy houſe, where the Sonne of God in glory, is light vnto their eyes, muſicke vnto their eares, ſweetnes vnto their taſt, and full contentment vnto their hearts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where, in ſeeing, they ſhall know him; and in knowing they ſhall poſſeſſe him; &amp; in poſſeſſing, ſhall loue him: and in louing, ſhall receiue eternall bleſſedneſſe, that bleſſed eternity, the Garland we run for, and the crowne we fight for. In a word. Here we ſhall come vnto the end of all our deſires, for what elſe is our end, but to come to that endles glory which hath no end.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Queene</hi> of <hi>Sheba,</hi> when ſhe had ſeene the<note place="margin">1. Ki <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> riches and royalty of <hi>Salamons</hi> Court, ſhe ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the King: It was a true word, which I heard in mine owne land, of thy proſperity &amp; happineſſe: but now I haue ſeene it with mine eies, lo, the one halfe is not told mee: ſo concerning the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fruition of eternity, in the life to come, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer may poſſiblie he deliuered by the tongues of men, yet vndoubtedly the one halfe cannot bee told vs.</p>
                     <p>By this place of Scripture (thus riſing by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees) the <hi>Kathariſtes,</hi> the family of Loue, and the <hi>Puritanes</hi> of our times, would gather this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.
<pb facs="tcp:180996:20"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:20"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:21"/>
Foraſmuch, as here are certaine degrees ſet downe, whereby Gods Church is builded, and whereby the members of the ſame do grow vp in Religion: therefore now in this life, by a Godly reformation, we may attaine vnto perfection.</p>
                     <p>This ſelfe conceited and head-ſtrong opinion of theirs, hath beene the firſt cauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ground of all the troubleſome contentions, which long ſince haue beene raiſed; and now (at this day) are continued in our Church. For diuers men, while they take themſelues (as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith) <hi>The Onely-wiſe men,</hi> and pure in their owne eyes, dreaming ſtill of a certaine imagined perfection, they neuer ceaſſe to bee clamorous to the Chriſtian Prince, troubleſome to the quiet ſtate, and diuers of them, very dangerous people, to the whole Church of God. In this verſe of our text, there is an end pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, there is a marke ſet vp, where-vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Chriſtian muſt labour to attaine, and ſtriue by all good endeuor, to come. But (alas) who can ſay that his heart is cleane? and man that is borne in ſinne, and conceaued in iniquity, while hee is clothed with ſinfull fleſh, how can he attaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection?</p>
                     <p>That the Militant Church of Chriſt hath had imperfections in all ages, it is a plaine and an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted truth. For, if euery me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber be imperfect, how can there be perfection in the whole? <hi>Perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>io noſtra magis conſtat remiſsione peccatorum, quàm</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:21"/>
                        <hi>perfectione virtutum.</hi> Our perfection conſiſteth (rather) in the forgiuenes of our ſinnes, then in the perfection of our vertues.</p>
                     <p>In truth, thus ſtands the eſtate of a Chriſtian mans life in this world.</p>
                     <p>As a man trauailing a long iournie, to a far cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, hee doth not continually go, but hee reſteth here, and ſtayeth there, hee baiteth in one place, and lodgeth all night in an other, yet ſtill hee is going forward, and holdeth on his iourney: ſo in this life, wee are pilgrims, wee are trauailers, and howſoeuer we do ſeek another countrie, and ſtriue to come vnto the Cittie of reſt, yet in this iournie wee wander often out of the way, wee take many falles, wee haue many impediments, neither is it poſſible, the light of our Faith ſhould ſtill hold out, and neuer bee darkned in this pilgrimage, till in the life to come, we be made Citizens of that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which is aboue.</p>
                     <p>Wee conclude then with the ſweet and modeſt ſaying of good Saint <hi>Auguſtine. Haec eſt perfectio Chriſtianorum, vt agnoſcant ſe nunquam eſse perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos.</hi> Herein ſtands the perfection of a Chriſtian, to acknowledge himſelfe, neuer to be perfect.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:180996:22"/>
                     <head>The Concluſion.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>Now it remaineth (as was promiſed in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) to ſhew the mutuali coherence of theſe words, and to knit vp againe the Lincks of this Chaine together,</p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere, in foure words, are contayned the foure cauſes of our ſaluation.</p>
                     <p>In <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> there is the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient cauſe, which is Gods loue. In <hi>Calling,</hi> there is the materiall cauſe, which is Chriſts death opened in his word. In <hi>Iuſtifying,</hi> there is the formall cauſe, aliuely faith: in <hi>Glorifying,</hi> there is the finall cauſe, which is euerlaſting life.</p>
                     <p>Thus, in <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> we behold <hi>God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> choſing of his loue: in <hi>Calling</hi>) we heare <hi>God the Sonne</hi> teaching by his word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in <hi>Iuſtifying;</hi> wee feele the comfort of <hi>God the holy Ghoſt:</hi> ſealing by his ſpirit. The fruite of all which: of Gods loue, choſing: of <hi>Chriſts word, Calling;</hi> of God the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> comforting: the effect of all theſe is our <hi>Glorifycation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>So that, as we do ſee farre with our bodily eye, yet reach farther with reaſon, which is the eye of
<pb facs="tcp:180996:22"/>
the mind, but Faith (which is the eye of the ſoule) out-ſtrippeth both: So, <hi>Calling</hi> enlightneth the mind with ſpirituall knowledge: <hi>Iuſtifying</hi> goeth further, and ſealeth vp the heart with heauenly comfort: <hi>Glorifying</hi> out-ſtrippeth all, and doth rauiſh the ſoule with immortalitie.</p>
                     <p>Euery one of vs, after this life, wee deſire, and hope to inioy eternall <hi>Glorie.</hi> Behold. <hi>Conceditur</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>in Predeſtinatione, promittitur in vocatione, oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur in Iuſtificatione, percipitur in Glorificatione.</hi> In <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> there is the firſt grant: In <hi>Calling,</hi> it is directly promiſed in <hi>Iustifying,</hi> it is plainely ſhewed: in <hi>Glorifying,</hi> there is liuerie and ſeiſin, the full poſſeſſion of all.</p>
                     <p>In <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> God beſtoweth vpon vs his loue: in <hi>Calling,</hi> he graunteth the bleſſing of his word in <hi>Iuſtifying,</hi> he yeelds the fruit of his ſpirit: in <hi>Glorifying,</hi> he doth wholy giue vnto vs himſelfe.</p>
                     <p>Here are the ſweet ſprings, iſſuing out of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> the head whereof cannot be found: here are the foure pleaſant riuers, which water Paradiſe, which runne through the Soule, with a Diuine vertue, and comfortably coole all our ſpirituall heat. Here is the holy and precious oyle, powred vpon the head of <hi>Aaron, the exceeding loue, and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ioh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> neſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> all</note> 
                        <hi>of grace,</hi> powred vpon our head Chriſt Ieſus, and running downe to the skirtes of his clothing, to euery particular, and penitent member of his Church.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:23"/>Here, wee may ſee the ſpirituall regeneration, of the Soule, ſhadowed out in the firſt creation of the World. In <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> there is the huge and vaſt deepe; the darke forme whereof could not be diſcerned: in <hi>Calling,</hi> the ſeparating of light, from darkneſſe; of knowledge, from ignorance in the Soule: in <hi>Iuſtifying,</hi> the <hi>Sunne</hi> is created; the<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 6</note> bright beames of his grace ſhine in our hearts: in <hi>Glorifying,</hi> we may behold the new <hi>Adam,</hi> fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 6</note> after the Image of God, and placed in the paradiſe of immortall ioy.</p>
                     <p>Obſerue here (if you pleaſe) the kindneſſe of alouing Father, who hauing many ſonnes, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſecret affection to ſome one, there is <hi>Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation:</hi> this affection in his good time hee decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, by making his will knowne, and his loue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, there is <hi>Calling:</hi> after this <hi>Calling,</hi> he cauſeth him to take vp his inheritance in Court, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him earneſt, in token of aſſurance, there is <hi>Iuſtifying:</hi> laſtly, he enters into his fathers ioy, and is made neire of all, there is <hi>Glorifying.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Againe, in <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> the heauenly huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band-man chooſeth out a plot of ground at his owne pleaſure in <hi>Calling,</hi> hee ſoweth it with the ſeede of his word: in <hi>Iuſtifying,</hi> hee waters, and cheriſheth it with his ſpirit: in <hi>Glorifying,</hi> hee reapes and carrieth into the barne.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, behold apparantly in <hi>Predeſtination,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 5.5</note> how <hi>Ioſeph</hi> long before was ſold into <hi>Egypt,</hi> by
<pb facs="tcp:180996:23"/>
the determinate Counſell of <hi>God:</hi> by <hi>Calling,</hi> how hee was looſed out of priſon, and deliuered from the bondage of ſinne: by <hi>Iuſtifying,</hi> how his cauſe was made knowne, and ſo acquitted innocent: in <hi>Glorifying,</hi> how hee was clothed in <hi>Purple,</hi> placed in the Kings Chariot, and made the chiefe of his Kingdome.</p>
                     <p>Now then, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the Romans: <hi>What ſhall wee ſay to theſe things?</hi> in like ſort, what ſhall we ſay to theſe ſo excellent, ſo ſweete, ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine miſteries? to theſe ſo comfortable teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Gods loue? to this Ladder of <hi>Iacobs,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon none but <hi>Angels</hi> do aſcend? to this inward working of the Spirit, which bloweth where it liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth? to this Diuine and hidden purpoſe, which can not be deceiued? to this ineffable glorie of the Sonnes of God, which they do expect and looke for? what ſhall wee ſay more effectuall, and more comfortable?</p>
                     <p>Can any thing bee ſet downe more plainely? or knit vp more briefly? can any demonſtration be concluded more ſoundly? Whom the Lord hath <hi>Predeſtinated,</hi> before all time, thoſe doth hee <hi>Call</hi> in time: whom he <hi>Calleth,</hi> thoſe hee doth <hi>Iuſtifie:</hi> and whome he <hi>Iuſtifieth,</hi> thoſe doth he <hi>Glorifie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus then, may euery true Chriſtian conclude, for the comfort of his Soule, and the aſſurance of his ſaluation for euer.</p>
                     <p>I am <hi>Iuſtified</hi> truely, by aliuely, and working
<pb facs="tcp:180996:24"/>
Faith, therefore I am <hi>Called:</hi> I am <hi>Called</hi> effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by his word, therefore, I am <hi>Predeſtinate:</hi> I am <hi>Predeſtinate,</hi> and choſen of his free loue, from eternitie, and therefore I ſhall bee <hi>Glorified</hi> vnto all eternitie againe.</p>
                     <p>Oſetled comfort, Oſweete conceiued hope of ioy: That ioy, which ſtrength of Hells ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, can neuer take away. Wherefore ſhould we feare? whereof ſhall we be afraid? No, no force ſo mightie, ſo puiſſant, able to ouerthrow vs. No ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of ſinne; no plagues of death, no rage of the world, no power of the Diuell himſelfe. In all theſe, we are more then conquerors. For al things ſhall turne to the beſt, to them, that are ſetled in Gods feare.</p>
                     <p>That wicked, and moſt dangerous conſpiracy, plotted againſt the Lords annointed, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it came to the very pinch, when it was brought to the very height, was not all turned topſie-turuie, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly diſapointed? This day wee do acknowledge it, with thankefull remembrance; this day, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee are all met together, in a moſt happie, and bleſſed peace; this day doth plainely witneſſe, that hee had the deliuerance, wee feele the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, the Church hath an endleſſe bleſſing, and God hath his euerlaſting praiſes.</p>
                     <p>O, behold what it is to bee knit vnto God. For whome he doth loue, who is able to wrong them whom he hath choſen, how can they be reiected?
<pb facs="tcp:180996:24"/>
whom hee doth <hi>Call,</hi> how ſhall they be ſhut out? whom hee doth <hi>Iuſtifie,</hi> who dare accuſe them? Whom God will <hi>Glorifie,</hi> how can they bee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken?</p>
                     <p>Seeing my ſoule is lincked to that <hi>Chaine,</hi> which can neuer be vnlooſed, my ſoule grounded vpon that foundation, which can neuer be ſhaken, what ſhall make vs to diſpaire? nay, what is it, ſhal make vs to wauer, or doubt of the ſingular loue of God, which he beareth towards vs, in his Sonne Chriſt Ieſus? What ſhall ſeparate vs, from the hope of immortalitie, in the life to come? ſhall the weariſomneſſe of this troubleſome life? ſhall the diſcontentments of this tranſitorie World? ſhall a litle ſickneſſe, ſhaking this brittle houſe of clay? No, all the afflictions of this life, which are but for a moment, they are not to be accounted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy that exceeding, ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> paſſing, eternall weight of glorie.</p>
                     <p>For God hath choſen vs before the world: he hath <hi>Called</hi> vs out of the World: he hath <hi>Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> vs in the World, and hee will <hi>Glorifie</hi> vs in the World to come.</p>
                     <p>God hath <hi>Choſen</hi> vs not being: hee hath <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> vs being enemies: hee hath <hi>Iuſtified</hi> vs, being ſinners and hee will <hi>Glorifie</hi> vs, being mortall wretches. Therefore we may cherefully ſing with <hi>Dauid. Miſericordia Domini, abaeterno in aeternum.</hi> The mercie of the Lord, is from euerlaſting, to
<pb facs="tcp:180996:25"/>
euerlaſting: Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euerlaſting <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting <hi>Glory,</hi> the one hauing no ending, the other hauing no beginning.</p>
                     <p>This bleſſed fruition of glorie, and immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that wee may feele the comfort of it, in our hearts and conſciences, now in this life, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after enioy in the life to come, the Lord grant, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for his bleſſed ſon Chriſt Ieſus ſake to whome with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt, three perſons, and one euerliuing God, be aſcribed all power, glory, praiſe, and thankes-giuing, for euer, and euer.</p>
                     <closer>Amen.</closer>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:180996:25"/>THE SECOND SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED BEFORE THE <hi>KING.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>BY <hi>ANT HONIE MAXEY,</hi> Batchelar in Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and Chaplaine to his Maieſtie in ordinarie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Points handled heerein are theſe.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>That there is an Hardening.</item>
                        <item>That God Hardeneth not.</item>
                        <item>How men become Hardened.</item>
                        <item>Moſt wofull to be Hardened.</item>
                        <item>The meanes to auoid it.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>G. Eld.</hi> for <hi>Clement Knight,</hi> dwelling in Paules Church-yard, at the ſigne of the holy Lambe. 1606.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:180996:26"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180996:26"/>
                  <head>HARDENING,</head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Exod. 10. 20.</bibl>
                        <q>And the Lord Hardened <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart, and hee did not let the children of Iſrael go.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>
                        <hi>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE heart of Man is deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and wicked aboue all</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iere. 17.</note> 
                        <hi>thnigs, who can knowe it?</hi> Although the Heart of man bee ſo little, that it will ſcarce ſerue a Kite for a baite, yet there are not more windings, nor more turnings in a Maze, or in a Laborinth, then are in the heart of man. The Heathen were ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in acknowledging a Diuine power, that rather than they would bee without a God, they gaue diuine honour to any kinde of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> worſhipped Idols; the <hi>Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> Starres; the <hi>Aegiptians</hi> Plants, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:180996:27"/>
of beaſts; the <hi>Graecians</hi> their owne conceits and the <hi>Romanes</hi> made their Cittie a ſhoppe for all kinde of Gods. So many were the windings, and ſo infinite the turnings of the Heathen, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching diuine worſhippe; that <hi>Varro</hi> obſerued in the world three thouſand Gods. The diſſolute and cunning Atheiſt, hee hath a fetch by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe alone, hee lets looſe the reines, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes the ſtreame of his ſenſuall affections, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee conceiues in his heart, and cleane contrary to the Heathen, ſaith there is no God at all. There is a third kinde, who though in<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>. 14. 1.</note> ſhowe they outwardly acknowledge God, yet they againe haue an other winding, ſecretly to themſelues: they plod on, ſwallowing any ſinne, for why? <hi>The Lord will neither do good nor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>h. 1. 12.</note> Becauſe there is not preſent puniſhment for euery ſinne. <hi>Tuſh all is well, no harme ſhall</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>. 10. 12.</note> 
                        <hi>happen vnto vs; For God careth not for any thing.</hi> Laſtly, in theſe our dayes, there is a fourth ſort, who haue a more ſtrange turning than all the former. For many hauing a generall notioh of Gods omnipotencie, hearing and reading ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of Gods <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Reprobation</hi> (whereof they vnderſtand no ground, nor conceiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right) they will preſume to commit any ſinne; for (ſay they) <hi>All is in God, no man can reſiſt his power, if hee hath choſen mee to life, I am ſure</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:27"/>
                        <hi>for one, if otherwiſe</hi> (as hee did with <hi>Pharaoh</hi>) hee hath appointed mee a <hi>Veſſell of his Wrath:</hi> it is not poſſibly to be auoyded.</p>
                     <p>Such are the windings, and theſe are the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings in the hearts, and ſecret thoughts of men: either, euery creature a God, or elſe no God; either a God that regarded not ſinne, or elſe a God that cauſeth vs to ſinne. <hi>Theſe turnings</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Eſa. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>and deuiſes in the ſight of the Lord, are eſteemed as clay before the Potter.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To conuince the Palpable errours of the three former, I holde it not conuenient: For, to thinke, there is any one heere preſent, who doth acknowledge no God at all, or ſuch a God, as regardeth not the actions of men, I hold it wrong to this holy aſſemblie, and I hope better things of this Chriſtian audience.</p>
                     <p>But to meete with this latter ſort, who leauing all good meanes of their ſaluation, do inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall a way from God, and yet in their willfull ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance would ſhift off, and ſhoue the cauſe of their condemnation vpon GOD. For ſuch chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, haue I vndertaken the expoſition of this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: in opening whereof I will touch theſe fiue points.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:28"/>Firſt that there is
<list>
                           <item>1 An hardening,</item>
                           <item>2 That God Hardeneth not.</item>
                           <item>3 How men become Hardened.</item>
                           <item>4 Moſt wofull to bee Hardened.</item>
                           <item>5 The meanes to auoidit.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:180996:28"/>
                     <head>There is an Hardening.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Oncerning this firſt point there are in the Scriptures two Greeke verbes, which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly vſed for this <hi>Hardening.</hi> The firſt is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, which doth properly ſignifie, to drie vp &amp; wither, vſed often in the 3. to the <hi>Hebrewes.</hi> 8. 13-15 verſes: <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Harden not your hearts.</hi> The other verbe in <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies to obdurate, or to make hard. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 18. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>They became ſtrangers from the life of God, through the hardneſſe of their hearts.</hi> Hauing thus recourſe vnto the Greeke tongue, wee ſhall ſee, that in the heart of man, firſt, there is a drying vp, and a certaine wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering: For in naturall things, and alſo in the ſoule, as there is a watering which is good and comfortable, ſo there is a drying vp, and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering, which is dangerous and hurtfull. In the earth there is a watering, for the hills are
<pb facs="tcp:180996:29"/>
the teates, and the ſprings the; milke to moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten, and to water the valleyes. <hi>Pſalme.</hi> 104. <hi>verſe</hi> 10. <hi>Hee ſendeth the ſprings into the riuers, which runne amongeſt the hilles.</hi> In the earth<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 20.</note> there is a drineſſe, for (ſaith <hi>Ioel) The people mourne for want of moiſture, the riuers of waters are dried vp, and the trees of the field are withered.</hi> In the body there is a wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, for the <hi>Liuer</hi> is the ſpring of bloud, that runneth into euery veine, and therefore <hi>Salomon</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 12. 7</note> calleth the <hi>Liuer the golden well.</hi> In the body, there is a withering, for <hi>Dauid</hi> complaineth in the <hi>Pſalme.</hi> 22. 15. <hi>verſe, My moyſture is like the drought in Summer, and my boanes are dryed vp like a pot-ſhard.</hi> As in the earth and bodie of man, ſo like wiſe in the ſoule, there is a wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and a withering. In the 4. of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> and 14. verſe, there is mention of a <hi>well of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing waters for the Soule.</hi> The preaching of<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 3. 6.</note> grace in Chriſt is called the <hi>watering of Apollo.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith, <hi>with ioy yee ſhall drawe</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 12. 3</note> 
                        <hi>waters out of the welles of Saluation.</hi> Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe, where this grace doth not water, there is withering. <hi>Si ſpiritus irrigatio defuerit, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> g. mag.</note> 
                        <hi>plantatio exareſcit.</hi> Euery planting that hath not the watering of Gods ſpirit, it withereth and dries away: therefore ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt, the</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 1. 3.</note> 
                        <hi>godly, they are like the tree planted by the riuers</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:29"/>
                        <hi>ſide,</hi> there is watering: <hi>but the vngodly are as a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den that hath no water, and as the Oaken leafe, that</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Eſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>fadeth,</hi> there is withering.</p>
                     <p>The other Greeke verbe is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies to harden. There bee <hi>Phiſieae and aethicae viciſſitudines,</hi> there is a naturall and a ſpirituall Philoſophie. In the naturall courſe of things, there is a congealing and an hardening, as of the yce and froſt, which <hi>Iob</hi> very fitly calleth <hi>the bands of Orion.</hi> becauſe, by the cold Eaſtern<note place="margin">Iob. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 31</note> and Northern windes the water becomes as a ſtoane, and the clods are bound together. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this <hi>Hardening,</hi> there is a melting. <hi>Hee,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 18<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>ſendeth out his word, and melteth them.</hi> As when the Froſt doth giue, and the ſhowers fall, which <hi>Iob</hi> calles in the ſame place, <hi>The ſweete influence of Pleiades.</hi> Both in nature, and in the ſoule alſo, there is a <hi>Reſoluing,</hi> and a <hi>Hardening: Deut.</hi> 32. <hi>verſe</hi> 2. The word is called <hi>Dewe,</hi> and there is a thaw or ſpirituall melting, when the heauenly dewe doth cauſe the ſoule to giue, and to reſolue into teares of Repentance: ſo in the 2. of <hi>Kings.</hi> 22. 10. <hi>Ioſias heart did melt, when he heard the Lawe read.</hi> When King <hi>Dauid</hi> had committed murther and adulterie, very grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſinnes; hee neuer be-thought himſelfe of the matter, but he began to congeale, and to bee <hi>Hardened</hi> in his ſinne. But aſſoone as the
<pb facs="tcp:180996:30"/>
Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> had awaked him, and his heart (like <hi>Gedeons fleece</hi>) had druncke vp the heauenly dewe, then preſently <hi>Dauid</hi> began to relent, his ſoule melted with ſorrow, and as appeareth in the 51. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> hee reſolued into teares of Repentance. <hi>Hezechias,</hi> when God had giuen vnto him a ſodaine and triumphant victorie ouer the hoſt of <hi>Zenacherib;</hi> preſently after, in the pride of his heart, hee forgat God, and began to congeale in ſinne: but as ſoone as the word of the Lord came vnto him by the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> then preſently his heart mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the bloud of his ſoule flowed forth in his repentant teares, as appeareth in the 38. of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay: hee turned his face vnto the wall, and wept bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 38. 3.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Nowe, as there is a <hi>Meiting,</hi> ſo alſo there is an <hi>Hardening</hi> in the ſoule, and that is, when the cuſtome of ſinne hath beaten ſuch an hard tracke, and ſo trampled the ſoule, that the word of God (the ſeede of life) cannot enter, This is expreſſed in the 13. of Saint <hi>Matthew.</hi> by the parable of the ſeede which fell by the high way ſide, where there was ſuch an hard way, ſuch a beaten path made by the common entrance of ſinne, that the ſeede could take no roote, but the diuell comes like an <hi>Harpie,</hi> and deuoureth it, before it can enter: For example
<pb facs="tcp:180996:30"/>
hereof, we wil take <hi>Cain,</hi> and King <hi>Pharao,</hi> whom my Text concerneth. <hi>Cain</hi> hauing ſlaine his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Abell,</hi> and committed horrible murther, the word of the Lord came vnto him ſaying: <hi>Where is thy brother Abell?</hi> Did <hi>Cains</hi> heart re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent? did hee confeſſe and ſay, I haue ſinned? or did hee reſolue into teares with <hi>Dauid?</hi> No ſuch matter: but firſt he anſwered with a foule word: <hi>I cannot tell where hee is:</hi> then hee deſpiſed the Lord to his face, as if hee ſhould ſay, you may go looke him, <hi>am I my brothers keeper?</hi> marke but this anſwere of <hi>Caine,</hi> and his cariage there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and you neede no other example of an heart that is <hi>Hardened:</hi> neither affection in kinred could touch him, nor ſhame of the world check him, nor the bloud of his ſlaine brother mooue him, nor the glorious preſence of the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſh him, nor the guilt of his owne thoughts raiſe him, nor (at laſt) the quickening word of God, which is powerfull to raiſe the very dead;<note place="margin">Hara Iob. 15.</note> none of theſe could any whit reuiue him. <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex circa praecordia ferrum,</hi> as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith of <hi>Leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athan: his heart was harder then the nether mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> when the word of God came vnto<note place="margin">Pha <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> him by <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> hee was ſo farre from yeelding, that hee ſeemed preſently as though hee would haue fought with God: <hi>Who is the</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:31"/>
                        <hi>Lord? I know no Lord, neither will I let Iſrael go.</hi> And whereas the word, and miracles ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with that word were ſufficient to conuince any liuing, <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart was ſo ſtonie, that though by a ſtrange Miracle, all the water in the land were become bloud, and did ſauour moſt vnholſomely, yet it is ſayd, <hi>Pharao went home,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 23</note> 
                        <hi>and all this could not enter into his heart,</hi> it could not pierce him. When the Prophet cryed to the Altar of <hi>Ieroboam, O Altar, Altar,</hi> heare the word of the Lord: <hi>the Altar heard, and claue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder.</hi> But the word of God which in <hi>Ieremie</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 13.</note> 23. 29. is called an <hi>Hammer,</hi> becauſe it bruſeth the ſtonie hearts of men: this <hi>Hammer</hi> with ten miracles gaue ten mighty ſtroakes at <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart, and yet it could neuer bruſe it.</p>
                     <p>Thus wee may plainely ſee, there is a <hi>wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> by Grace, and a <hi>melting</hi> by Gods word, as appeareth by <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Hezechiah,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued into teares: againe through want of Grace, there is a <hi>withering,</hi> and by cuſtome of ſinne, there is an <hi>Hardening,</hi> as in <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi> whoſe hearts the word of God could not pierce, but the more they were beaten on, the more hard and flintie they became.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:180996:31"/>
                     <head>God hardeneth not.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T Remayneth on the ſecond poynt to diſcuſſe, whether this <hi>Hardening</hi> bee of GOD? In opening whereof, it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrange to heare, how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truely, how vncharitablie we are charged by our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries: not onely <hi>Campion</hi> and <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> but eſpecially in certaine Articles, or <hi>Foreible rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> lately publiſhed: wherein it is directly ſet downe, that the proteſtants doe make God <hi>the author and onely cauſe of ſinne:</hi> that they deride <hi>Gods permiſſion;</hi> and plainely affirme, <hi>God is worſe</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Article. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>then the Denill, and ſo are bound in conſcience ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to aske God forgiueneſse for their ſinnes.</hi> Oh fearefull blaſphemie, and wordes vnſeemely Chriſtian eares: Where is modeſtie? where is trueth and Chtiſtian piety? Is this our doctrine? doe we thus teach? no verily: both in worde and writing we acknowledge the Lord our God
<pb facs="tcp:180996:32"/>
to bee full of compaſſion and loue, the bowels of his mercie ſweet and amiable, hee would not the death of any, hee is gracious and kinde, gentle and readie to forgiue, and (to the death) wee affirme, more then moſt holy, pure and iuſt are all his workes and wayes: therefore the Lord be iudge betweene them and vs, and lay not this ſinne vnto their charge.</p>
                     <p>Touching this doctrine, how ſinne firſt came to bee: how it came in, where it firſt tooke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and that God is not the author of it, I haue ſhewed heretofore in handling the <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ine,</hi> the meanes of our ſaluation: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the Diuell was <hi>Primitiuus peccator,</hi> the<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 6.</note> firſt offender for hee ſinned from the beginning. So that from him ſinne firſt boyleth vp, as out of the maine Sea. From Sathan when it comes to <hi>Adam,</hi> it ariſeth as out of a Spring: from this Spring it is reſerued in nature as in a Conduit, from nature conueied to concupiſence (as by a pipe,) and from thence doth flow all the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe and wickedneſſe that is in the life of man. Well then: if ſinne doe proceede from the ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion of Sathan working through our owne concupiſcence, and ſo God wholy freed from all imputation of euill: why is it ſo often ſaid in the Scripture. <hi>Deut.</hi> 2. 30. <hi>And the Lord hardened the heart of</hi> Sihon <hi>King of</hi> Heſhbon, <hi>and made</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:32"/>
                        <hi>him obſtinate:</hi> Ioſhua the 11. 20. <hi>It came of the Lord to harden their hearts:</hi> and here often in the booke of <hi>Exodus, and the Lord hardened the heart of Pharao.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To make this plaine: it is a point well knowne vnto the learned, that this ſpeech (where it is ſaid) <hi>God hardened.</hi> The Hebrew Dialect doth<note place="margin">Flaccu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Illiric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> P. Lon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> li. 1. di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Tho A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> quin. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 23. arti <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> ſignifie a permiſſion, and not an action. Verbes that ſignifie to doe, they often expreſſe a ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and not a doing. <hi>Deſtruit cum deſerit:</hi> God is then ſaid to <hi>Harden,</hi> when hee doth forſake. <hi>Impios cùm non retrahit a malo culpae, dicitur di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittere.</hi> As the enduing with grace is the effect of Gods <hi>Election,</hi> ſo the with-holding of his grace is the effect of <hi>Reprobation. Dei includere eſt, clauſis non aperire,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> vpon the 12. of <hi>Iob.</hi> and foureteenth verſe. Euery action hath his qualitie from the roote of the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and from the intention of the <hi>Author: De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us autem (quoad peccatum) non habet poſitiuè velle, ſed tantùm priuatiuè,</hi> Touching ſinne, God hath no <hi>Poſitiue</hi> will, but onely in regard of former ſinnes a <hi>Priuation</hi> of his grace. To bee ſhort: God doth <hi>Harden,</hi> as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Aguſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> ſaith: <hi>Non malum obtrudendo, ſed gratiam non concedendo:</hi> not by cauſing vs to commit ſinne, but by not graunting vnto vs his grace. I, but how comes it to paſſe, that wee aſ well as others)
<pb facs="tcp:180996:33"/>
are not partakers of Gods grace? why haue not wee alſo his good Spirit to direct and guide vs? Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> makes it plaine againe. <hi>Non ideo</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>non habet homo gratiam, quia Deus non dat, ſed quia homo non accipit:</hi> men become <hi>Hardened,</hi> and want the ſpirit of grace, why? not becauſe God doth not offer it vnto them, but becauſe they receiue it not, when it is offered. For exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: One of vs being ſicke, and like to die, the Phiſician knowing our caſe, hee takes with him ſome preſeruation to comfort vs, and comes to the doore and knocks, if wee will not, or bee not able to let him in, wee periſh and die, and the cauſe is not in the Phiſician, but in our ſelues that let him not in. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Sinne is<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> de 10.</note> a diſeaſe, whereof we are all ſicke, for we haue all ſinned: <hi>Romanes.</hi> 6. 12. verſe. Chriſt, he is the Phiſician of our ſoules: <hi>Venit de coelo magnus me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicus,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 9. 12.</note> 
                        <hi>quia per totum vbique iacebit aegrotus.</hi> Chriſt the great Phiſicion came downe from heauen, becauſe all mankind was generally infected. Hee comes to the doore of our hearts, and there hee knocks. <hi>Reuel.3.20. Behold, I ſtand at the doore</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 6. 35.</note> 
                        <hi>and knocke,</hi> Hee bringeth with him <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, the bread of life, his eternall word to comfort vs, if we let him in: if we open the doore of our hearts, he will come in, and ſuppe with vs, as hee did with <hi>Mary,</hi> and forgiue vs all our ſinnes.<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 10.</note>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:33"/>
but if wee will not, or through long contagion of our ſinne bee not able to let Chriſt in, we die in our ſinnes: and the caſe is euident, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt doth not offer grace, and comfort vnto vs, but becauſe wee receiue it not, when it is offered. <hi>Meritò perit aegrotus, qui non medicum vocat, ſed vltrò venientem reſpuit:</hi> worthily doth<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> that ſicke patient periſh, who will neither ſend for the Phiſicion himſelfe, nor accept of his help, when it is offered.</p>
                     <p>More plainely thus, in the foureteenth of Saint <hi>Mathew.</hi> Our Sauiour walking on the Sea, hee bad Saint <hi>Peter</hi> come vnto him: who walking on the water, ſeeing ſtorme and tempeſtariſe, his heart fayled, and hee began to ſincke: vpon his cry vnto our Sauiour, hee preſently ſtretched forth his hand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> tooke him into the ſhippe, and ſaued him. This world (wee know by dayly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) it is a ſea of trouble and miſerie: our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour (as hee ſayd to Saint <hi>Peter</hi>) ſo moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly hee willeth euery one of vs to come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: as wee walke, ſtormes and tempeſts doe ariſe, through frailtie of our fleſh, and the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our Faith, wee begin to ſincke, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour hee ſtretcheth forth his hand, hee giueth vs <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> his <hi>Word,</hi> his <hi>Sacraments,</hi> the good motions of his ſpirit, to ſaue vs from ſinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and to keepe vs in the ſhippe of his Church:
<pb facs="tcp:180996:34"/>
if wee refuſe theſe meanes, we periſh, we ſincke in our ſinnes, why? not becauſe Chriſt doth not moſt kindly put forth his hand vnto vs, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in want and diſtreſſe wee lay not hold vpon him. <hi>This is condemnation, that light is come into the world men refuſe it, &amp; loue darkneſſe more then light.</hi> Our bleſſed Sauiour with great louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 3. 19.</note> hee doth inuite all men to his <hi>Great Supper,</hi> if wee make excuſes, or wilfully refuſe to come, he may iuſtly pronounce, <hi>none of thoſe that were bidden ſhall euer taſt of my ſupper.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 14. 24</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Therefore let not men deceiue themſelues, and complaine, as though God did harden their hearts and deny them grace and mercy, for as <hi>Ionas</hi> ſaith in his ſecond Chapter, and 8. verſe.<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 2. 8.</note> 
                        <hi>They forſake their owne mercie. Deus prior in amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> God neuer hateth vntill he be firſt hated: and ſo<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>broſe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>no eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tit n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> i di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> it. Aug <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eſſi.</note> I conclude with Saint <hi>Ambroſe: Nemo tibi Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum poteſt auferre, niſi te illi auferas:</hi> no man can ſeparate Chriſt from thee, except firſt thou doeſt ſeperate thy ſelfe from him.</p>
                     <p>This is plainely to bee obſerued in <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> had hee (being long before peaceably ſetled in a rich and mighty Kingdome) made right vſe of the bleſſings of God: had hee at the firſt, or oftentimes after, yeelded vnto the word of the Lord, he had neuer come to the ſtate of <hi>Hardening,</hi> nor left himſelfe ſuch a fearefull
<pb facs="tcp:180996:34"/>
ſpectacle of Gods wrath for euer. But <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> feeling wealth and reuenew comming ſo faſt and aboundantly, that he builded new Citties (<hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Exo. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> and <hi>Raamſes</hi> (to lay vp his treaſures, his heart was ſo bent and ſet vpon Couetouſneſſe (ſuch multitudes of people moyling and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in ſundry workes for his profit) that in no<note place="margin">Exod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> Cha. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> caſe hee could endure to heare of their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Firſt, he ſaid flatly, they ſhould not go. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, hee ſought to ſhift off the matter, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the miracle not to be done by Gods hand, but by inchantment. Thirdly, hee yeldeed<note place="margin">8. 25.</note> they ſhould offer ſacrifice, but onely in his owne land. Fourthly, hee was content they ſhould go ſacrifice out off his land (but ſtill hee would condition with God (<hi>None but the</hi>
                        <note place="margin">10. 11. 10. 24.</note> 
                        <hi>men ſhould go.</hi> Fiftly, the men ſhould go, the Women go, the Children go, but their ſheepe and Oxen (wherein their wealth ſtood) ſhould not go.</p>
                     <p>Thus <hi>Pharaoh</hi> (through a wretched and gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple minde (neuer left winding and turning, dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying and preſuming of the Lords mercie, and patience, till adding one ſinne vnto another, his heart became <hi>Hardened.</hi> Nay notwithſtanding ſo many miracles, and that before hee confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Lord to bee God, <hi>He and his people ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> and earneſtly deſired <hi>Moſes</hi> to pray for him,
<pb facs="tcp:180996:35"/>
yet contrarie to his owne thoughts, and againſt<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> eure howe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> eſull a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> g it is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> ully <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> nne a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>ſt our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> e con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce.</note> his owne knowledge, when hee ſaw the people of Iſrael were gone, hee flies to ſtrength of war, hee cals his Captaines, hee muſters his people, hee gathers his Chariots, hee purſues with all might and maine, till at laſt both hee and his (ouerwhelmed in the ſea) receaued the fearefull and finall iudgement of wilfull diſobedience. Now then let all the earth know the goodneſſe of the Lord, and wiſely obſerue his loue vnto mankinde for euer. It is true, <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart was <hi>Hardened,</hi> and hee with his Nobles vtterly ouerthrowne. But, before this ouerthrow, all meanes poſſible that could bee, were vſed to winne <hi>Pharao.</hi> Bleſſing vpon bleſſing before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued; puniſhment vppon puniſhment after in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted; <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtill and againe prayed for him; <hi>Aaron</hi> euer and anon perſwaded him; the plagues to aſtoniſh him, were ſodaine and exceeding won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull. the deliuerance, to winne him, was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and more miraculous: the <hi>Enchanters</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, the <hi>People</hi> cryed out, his <hi>Seruants</hi> were offended, <hi>Aegypt</hi> was almoſt quite deſtroyed the land of <hi>Goſhen</hi> was ſtill vntouched: God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and againe, and ſtill againe was entreated, and yet <hi>Pharao</hi> remained obſtinate. Shall we then ſay, that God <hi>Hardened Pharaohs</hi> heart? Bee it farre from vs: for it is directly ſet downe in the
<pb facs="tcp:180996:35"/>
ninth Chapter. 34. verſe. <hi>And when Pharao ſaw the haile and thunder were gone, hee ſinned againe, &amp; Hardened his heart.</hi> And againe the 8. Chap. 15. verſe. <hi>When Pharao ſaw that he had reſt, he har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened his owne heart.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Oh, I would to God it were onely <hi>Pharaohs</hi> caſe, and that wee alſo being Chriſtians did not abuſe the long forbearance, and much louing kindneſſe of our God. For, now feare of the ſtorme is ouer, but euen one yeare or two: now that our louing God through his vnſpeakable mercie hath ſo ſweetely ſet all in order, that all Nations round about vs ſtand amazed; now that he hath ſetled amongſt vs a moſt happie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious<note place="margin">Behold our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> nes to G <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> enjoying ſo religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and peaceable a Prince.</note> peace, now that hee hath giuen honour, plentie, and reſt throughout all the Land, ſtil, ſtil wee dally and trifle with the Lord: according to our priuate humors, and ſeuerall ſectes, we will not profeſſe the Goſpell, except we firſt condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (as <hi>Pharao</hi> did) both with our God &amp; King: with humble hearts we do not ſubmit our ſelues peaceably to ſerue the Lord: For this bleſſed <hi>Cataſtrophe,</hi> our ſoules flame not with thankeful loue, neither (as they ought) breake forth into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting praiſes: Nay, whereas the word of God came ten times to <hi>Pharao,</hi> willing him to let the people of Iſraell go, &amp; ſerue the Lord, the ſame word comes an hundred times ten to our
<pb facs="tcp:180996:36"/>
hearts, crying and beating vpon vs to haue vs let go our contentions, our carnal and peruerſe affections, and yet we neuer relent at the ſame. <hi>A mans heart will tell him more then ſeuen watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>. 37.</note> 
                        <hi>in a trwer:</hi> We know, we know (euery one in his owne boſome) the ſinnes which we ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foſter, and will not let go. But as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth the Iewes, <hi>Hebrewes</hi> 3. 12. ſo I aduiſe you in the name of God. <hi>Take heede, take heede, leaſt in any of you there be found a falſe and an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill heart, to depart from the liuing God.</hi> For aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly, it is a fearefull and bitter thing to carry euer a ſelfe-wilde and peruerſe mind, to reſpect meerely the applauſe of men, and fading plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this life; ſo, inwardly falling away from God, and looſing the bleſſed comfort of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. O Sauiour ſweete, and ſecret hope, turne vs, that we may be turned; bow our hearts, and the hearts of our ſeede vnto thee, that we may feare thy iudgements, acknowledge thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and ſtand faſt in thy loue for euer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:180996:36"/>
                     <head>How men become Hardened.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He third point is, to ſhew how men become <hi>Hardened:</hi> in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening whereof, we are to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that there are three ſorts of <hi>Hardenings: Naturalis, Voluntaria, Iudicialis.</hi> The firſt is by <hi>Nature,</hi> the ſecond by <hi>habite</hi> and <hi>Cuſtome,</hi> the third by the <hi>Iuſt iudgement of God.</hi> The firſt is the forgetfulnes or dulneſſe in a natural man, when he ouerſhootes him ſelfe, for want of wiſe obſeruation and remembrance.</p>
                     <p>In the ſixth of <hi>Marke,</hi> our Sauiour Chriſt fed<note place="margin">Mar. 6.</note> fiue thouſand men with fiue loaues and two fiſhes, a miracle ſufficient to proue vnto his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, that hee was the Sonne of God. Yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after, when he came walking on the Sea, and cauſed the winde to ceaſe, they ſtood ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and did not acknowledge his <hi>Diuinity:</hi> for<note place="margin">Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren may be blind in mind, hardened in heart for a tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> (ſaith the ſcripture) in the 52. verſe. They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered not the miracle of the loaues, becauſe <hi>their hearts were hardened:</hi> that is, through natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall imperfection they had forgot it.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, there is an <hi>Hardening</hi> by <hi>habit,</hi> when
<pb facs="tcp:180996:37"/>
(through a careleſſe ſecuritie) men doe continue in ſinne, &amp; take ſuch a cuſtome, as they can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leaue. So <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> his heart by cuſtome was ſo long bent, and ſet vpon couetouſneſſe, that being conuerſant amongſt the Apoſtles, and daily imployed in moſt diuine and holy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: yet euen then, his mind and thought ſtill ranne vpon money, vpon gaine. This is <hi>Habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alis obduratio,</hi> an <hi>Hardening</hi> which growes by continuance in ſinne. Hee that is in this caſe, it ſtands him vpon to gather vp his ſpirits, and ſtrongly to reſiſt ſinne, to ſequeſter himſelfe oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vnto deuout and priuate Meditations, to ioy in hearing the word, with reuerence to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the bleſſed Sacraments, eſpecially to bee feruent in prayer, for ſo Saint <hi>Peter</hi> willed <hi>Simon Magus: Repent and pray, that (if it bee poſsible) the thoughts of thy heart may bee forgiuen thee.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> ts. 8. 22.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The third and laſt is <hi>Iudicialis obduratio, an Hardning which proceedes from the iuſt iudgement of God. Cùm peccatum fit paena peccati,</hi> when ſinne becomes a puniſhment to him that commiteth it, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> m. 1. 2. 7</note> offormer errours, when the thought is ſo poyſoned, the mind and ſoule ſo generally infected, that the ſpirit of God is vtterly quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: no light of nature, no priuate Counſell, no publike exhortation out of the word, no inward
<pb facs="tcp:180996:37"/>
motions of Gods ſpirit can preuaile, but hee go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on ſo long, &amp; is ſo far ſpent, that being paſt all feare to offend, careleſly he maketh no ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of any ſin whatſoeuer, till at length finding in himſelfe no hope of recouery, either God ſtrikes him apparently with his iudgement, as he did <hi>Pharao,</hi> or elſe by his death hee paſſeth ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to the graue without repentance, as <hi>Diues,</hi> or in this life (as <hi>Iudas</hi> did) doth plunge himſelfe in the gulfe of deſperation. This is that <hi>Harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> which is here meant of <hi>Pharao.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This <hi>Hardening</hi> is not all on a ſuddaine: <hi>Non ruimus primo impetu, vt Deo reluctemur,</hi> no man is <hi>Hardened</hi> at the firſt. <hi>Nemo fit repentè miſer.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Calu.</note> 
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 13. <hi>Take heed leaſt any of you be Hardened through the deceitfulneſse of ſinne.</hi> The <hi>deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinne,</hi> it creepeth like a canker-worme, it gathers, it ſteales vpon vs, and ſo vnder the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge of God, men come vnto <hi>Hardening</hi> by degrees. <hi>Naturalis eſt ordo, vt abimperfecto,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Tho. Aq <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>ad perfectu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quis moueatur.</hi> It is a naturall courſe euen in euill (ſaieth the ſchooleman) by degrees to come vnto perfection. <hi>As they that dwell in</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 84.</note> 
                        <hi>Gods houſe, will bring forth more fruite, and then appeare before the God of Gods in perfect beautie.</hi> ſo, on the contrary, the wicked are not <hi>Hardened</hi> all at once, but as they offend more and more, ſo by little and little they grow to the height of
<pb facs="tcp:180996:38"/>
ſinne, and as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>they do fall from one ſinne to another.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iudas</hi> was firſt a cunning <hi>Diſsembler,</hi> ſecondly,<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> at. 26. 8.</note> he became a ſecret <hi>Thiefe;</hi> thirdly, he grew to be<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>. 12. 5.</note> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> t. 26. 25 48.</note> an impudent <hi>Lyar;</hi> fourthly, he proued a bolde <hi>Traitor;</hi> laſtly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a deſperate <hi>Reprobate.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> at. 27. 5.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The diſeaſes of the body, they do not grow at one &amp; the ſelfe-ſame time they do firſt appeare but by ryot, &amp; diſtemperature vſed long before: ſo the ſoule infected with vncleane thoughts, and in youth accuſtomed to euill actions, at length commeth to the vncurable diſeaſe of <hi>Hardening.</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in the 8. of his <hi>Confeſſ.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Aug. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ſſ 8.</note> doth open this point very plainely.</p>
                     <p>Firſt the deuill by concupiſcence ſuggeſteth euill thoughts: euill thoughts egge on delight: delight tolleth on conſent: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent engendereth action: action bringeth forth cuſtome: cuſtome groweth to neceſſity: and neceſſity in ſinning is the forerunner of death. For example. Firſt the diuell ſuggeſteth euill thoughts, ſo hee did vnto <hi>Eue,</hi> hee wound her in by tainting her thought, by telling her ſhe ſhould haue <hi>al knowledge, and be as God:</hi> this euill thought egged on delight; for as appearethin the ſixth verſe, the Apple grew pleaſant in her eyes: this delight tolled on conſent: for then ſhe tooke of the fruite: laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of conſent came the action, for ſhee did
<pb facs="tcp:180996:38"/>
eate and gaue it to her huſband.</p>
                     <p>Now, when the action of ſin is committed, there doth not preſently follow <hi>Hardening:</hi> for, if the heart do melt &amp; thaw, if the ſoule do giue &amp; reſolue into teares of repentance for the ſame, then there is no <hi>Hardening.</hi> But, if from one acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on committed, we come vnto another, and ſo to the cuſtome &amp; continuance in ſin, then are we ſnared with the cords of our owne iniquity, and fettered with this chaine, againſt the general day of Gods iudgement. To make this plaine, I will ſhow you by ſeuen degrees, as it were by ſeuen ſtayres, how men do deſcend into this pitte of <hi>Hardening.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The firſt ſtep is <hi>importabile:</hi> Sin at the firſt, it is<note place="margin">1 Import <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> bile.</note> importable, it ſeemes vntollerable to be borne. One that hath bin religiouſly brought vp, hath bin accuſtomed to a milde and honeſt conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and hath ben feareful to offend: at length, if through bad co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, through his own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and the allurements of Sathan, hee falleth into any foule ſin; at the firſt it is importable, it doth ſtrike ſuch an horror into him, that he is in a wofull taking and grieuouſly tormented. This we may ſee by <hi>Dauid,</hi> who hauing alwaies a tender conſcience, loath to offend, yet after o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertaken by committing murder and adulter, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſoone as he ſaw what he had done, hee was
<pb facs="tcp:180996:39"/>
mightily troubled, whereſoeuer he became, his offence ſo ſtucke in his thought, that in the 51. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3. he cryeth out, <hi>my ſin is euer before me,</hi> that is, is continually in my ſight.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond ſtayre is <hi>Graue, heauie:</hi> for ſinne<note place="margin">2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> ue.</note> being committed twiſe or thriſe, it is not as it was at the firſt, importable, but it is heauie. Hee ſorrowes, and is grieued, but hee is nothing ſo troubled in mind, nor afflicted in conſcience as he was before.</p>
                     <p>The third ſtayre is <hi>Leue light.</hi> For he that hath<note place="margin">3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> vſed himſelf more often to ſin that which at the firſt was importable, and afterwards heauie, at length becommeth light. This appeareth by the vnchaſt woman ſpoken off in the Prouerbs, who hauing had ſome practiſe in ſinne, ſhe makes no more matter of it, but lightly paſſeth it ouer with <hi>wiping her mouth,</hi> &amp; ſaith <hi>ſhe hath not ſinned.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>. 30. 20.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The fourth ſtayre is <hi>inſenſible, paſt feeling,</hi> for<note place="margin">4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> nſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> after that ſin be made light of, and that there be no remorſe nor griefe for ſinne, then they grow paſt feeling: ſuch were the Iſraelites of whom the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſpeaketh in his 5. Chap. and 3. ver. <hi>Thou haſt ſmitten them, but they haue not ſorrowed, for they haue made their faces harder then a ſtone,</hi> that is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they haue ſinned ſo long, that now they are paſt feeling.</p>
                     <p>The fift ſtaire is <hi>Delectabile.</hi> When men take<note place="margin">5 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:39"/>
pleaſure in ſin (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith) <hi>They reioyce in</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pro. 2. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>doing euill, and delight in wickedneſſe.</hi> Heereof Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith. <hi>Tum eſt conſummata infoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitas, vbi turpia non ſolùm committuntur, ſede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam delectant:</hi> Then is the eſtate of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion certaine, when foule ſinnes are not onely commited, but are delightfull alſo.</p>
                     <p>The ſixt ſtaire is <hi>Deſiderabile,</hi> when (through<note place="margin">6 Deſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile.</note> delight) men grow to ſuch a cuſtome, that they inwardly deſire to ſin, ſo that as S. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaid: <hi>Si nunquam moreretur<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nunqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vellepeccare deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neret:</hi> ſuch a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if he ſhould neuer die, he would neuer ceaſe to ſin, for though he did not commit it in action, yet ſtill he would deſire it in thought.</p>
                     <p>The ſeauenth ſtaire is <hi>defenſibile. When hee hath</hi>
                        <note place="margin">7 Defenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile.</note> 
                        <hi>gotten a forehead of braſſe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſay.</hi> 48. 4. as the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> ſaith) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tyrant doth boaſt that he can<note place="margin">Pſal. 1. 1.</note> do miſchiefe, <hi>when hee ſits in the ſeate of the ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> when hee doth not onely by habit deſire to ſin, and delight in it, but nowe he will take vpon him to defend it. <hi>Peccatum porta mortis, defenſio</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Origen.</note> 
                        <hi>eſt lumen inferni,</hi> Sin is the high way to death, but the defence of ſin is the very next ſtep into hell. At this point were the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued for idolatry, <hi>the Scripture ſaith,</hi> they ſaid <hi>deſperately,</hi> we haue <hi>loued ſtrange Gods, and them will we follow againe they refuſed to hearken, and pulled away the ſhoulder, &amp; ſtopped their eares, and</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Zach. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:40"/>
                        <hi>made their hearts as an Adamant ſtone. Impius cùm</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 2. 25. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>0. 18. 3.</note> 
                        <hi>venerit in profundum, contemnit:</hi> a diſſolute liuer once growne to the height of ſin, becomes deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate.</p>
                     <p>Thus Sin, firſt it is <hi>importable,</hi> ſecondly, <hi>heauie,</hi> thirdly it becomes <hi>light,</hi> fourthly <hi>paſt feeling,</hi> fift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>delightfull,</hi> ſixtly <hi>deſired,</hi> and laſtly to be <hi>defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi> Here is <hi>deſcenſus Auerni,</hi> theſe be the ſtayres that lead to the chambers of death, &amp; the ſteps<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wherby the reprobate do deſcend vnto final de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Indeed, at the firſt, when ſin is <hi>impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table,</hi> &amp; that we are wonderfully grieued for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of it, there is great hope of recouery, &amp; he that ſo feeling the wound of ſinne, doth there ſtay the courſe of it, it is an excellent ſigne of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Initium ſalutis notitia peccati,</hi> the firſt ſtep of repentance is the firſt finding out, &amp; acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of ſin. In the ſecond of the <hi>Acts,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſaw and knew their ſin, they cried out, <hi>Men &amp; brethern, what ſhal we do to be ſaued.</hi> This hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, this troubled mind, it made them ſeeke for comfort, and ſo brought them to repentance. Secondly, when ſin is a burden vnto our ſoules, ſo that we would faine be eaſed of it, there is yet good hope. We may ſee it by <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 38. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 4. verſe. <hi>Mine iniquities are gone ouer mine head, and are as a burden too heauy for mee to beare.</hi> The weight of this burden made <hi>Dauid</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:40"/>
in the 18. ver. following, <hi>to confeſſe his wickednes, and to be ſory for his ſin,</hi> it made him flie vnto God for eaſe. <hi>O caſt your burden vpon the Lord, for he will not ſuffer the righteous to fall for euer.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thirdly, when men make light of ſin, ſurely danger is not far off, <hi>for a threefold cord is not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily broken, and the third letting of bloud in the ſame veine, is exceeding dangerous:</hi> but yet ſtill there is ſome hope, for though in the hot chaſe of our blinde and youthful deſires, though then for a time we account it a light matter, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this or that ſinne, yet God may touch our hearts, <hi>Chriſt may looke backe vpon vs, as he did on S. Peter, who denied him thrice.</hi> His word may ſo ſtrike vs, that we may come to know our ſelues, to ſee in what caſe we are, to bewaile our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, &amp; ſo turne vnto god by praier &amp; repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. <hi>All theſe things</hi> (as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith) <hi>will God worke twice</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iob. 33. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> O bew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> and ſin more.</note> 
                        <hi>or thrice with a man.</hi> But if we come to <hi>Inſenſibile,</hi> the fourth ſtayre, ſo that we grow <hi>paſt feeling,</hi> we ſin daily and haue no ſenſe of it, if there be no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe, no griefe nor diſlike of ſin, wo be vnto vs, 2. <hi>Amos. 6. For three tranſgreſſions, and for foure, I will not turne to Iſrael,</hi> ſaith the Lord. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the infinite and extraordinary mercie of God we are the ſons of wrath, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> followeth this deadlie wound of <hi>Hardening.</hi> It is a principle in Phiſicke <hi>grauiſsimè is aegrotat, qui ſe non ſentit</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:41"/>
                        <hi>aegrotare:</hi> if a man bee ſicke, and know it not, out of queſtion, hee is very dangerouſly and deadly ſicke: hee that findes in himſelfe no want of any thing (as the Church of <hi>Laodicea</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, I ſtand not in need of any thing. This dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uel. 3. 17</note> this vnfeeling numneſſe, it is a plaine fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teller of death: for example, if a man haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a grieuous wound in his body, if it ake, if it pricke and ſhoote, if it paine him, eyther it is healing, or elſe there is hope to heale it: but (as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith) <hi>Quod non dolet, non pro</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
                        <hi>ſano, ſed pro mortuo computandum,</hi> if the wound be ſuch, that it neuer cauſeth griefe, if it neuer ake nor ſmart, vndoubtedly it is dead fleſh, of neceſſitie it muſt be cut off.</p>
                     <p>To commit actuall and preſumptuous ſinnes, when a mans owne knowledge and Gods ſpirit cryeth in him to the contrary, theſe are wounds and grieuous woundes vnto the ſoule, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hath gone on ſo far, that he doth delight in theſe ſinnes, ſo often, ſo long, that his minde is neuer troubled, his thoughts neuer checked, his ſoule neuer grieued, ſurely ſuch a one (being vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly <hi>paſt feeling</hi>) is very neere to this fearefull e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of <hi>hardening.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus haue I ſhewed how, and after what ſort men become <hi>Hardened,</hi> not of my ſelfe, but as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith: <hi>Ligatus teneor non ferro alieno;
<pb facs="tcp:180996:41"/>
ſed meaferrea voluntate: velle meum tenebat ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micus, et inde mihi funes fecerat, et conſuetudini, dum non reſiſtitur, fact a eſt neceſsitas.</hi> A man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes <hi>hardened,</hi> he is fettered, not by any other chaine, but by the cordes of his owne ſinne, the deuill by deceit gets power ouer the will, and ſo doth ſnare vs, and becauſe in the beginning wee did not reſiſt cuſtome, at length it groweth to neceſſity. This is the very ſame in effect ſetdown by Saint <hi>Paule</hi> in the 4. to the <hi>Epheſians</hi> 18. where this manner of <hi>Hardening</hi> is alſo expreſſed. firſt <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, the minde is <hi>darkened,</hi> they cannot rightly diſcerne what to do, then, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, they become ignorant, thirdly, comes in <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, when the ſoule (for want of heauenly dewe) beginnes to <hi>wither</hi> and <hi>harden,</hi> fourthly <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>paſt feeling,</hi> and laſtly giuen ouer to <hi>commit all ſinne with greedineſſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:180996:42"/>
                     <head>Moſt wofull to be hardened.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow, what a grieuous and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable eſtate is it to be <hi>har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened,</hi> let it pleaſe you with patience to obſerue a while &amp; you ſhall briefely vnderſtand. The comfort of mans life in this world, it conſiſteth in the enioying, either of temporall or ſpirituall bleſſings. But the ſtrong man hauing once got poſſeſſion, when a man is fallen away from grace, and his heart <hi>Hardened<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> how fearefull, how mournfull a caſe it is? it may manifeſtly appeare in this; for that ſuch men, they can haue no true ioy of temporall things in this world, nor any true comfort of the ſweete graces in the life to come.</p>
                     <p>Firſt concerning ſpirituall bleſſings: There is nothing more cheerefull vnto man, then the knowledge of his minde, nothing more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in him then the light of his vnderſtanding.
<pb facs="tcp:180996:42"/>
This knowledge, this light of nature, this vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and iudgement is vtterly extinguiſhed. <hi>Suffocatur naturae lumen, cùm ad huius abiſſi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſum</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>accedimus:</hi> the light of nature is choked, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they once enter into this gulf of <hi>Hardning.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In man there is a threefold light. The light of the body which is the <hi>Eye,</hi> the light of the mind which is <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> the light of the ſoule,<note place="margin">Eph. 1, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 1 Cor. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> by which we diſcerne <hi>things that are not ſeene.</hi> In the obſtinate <hi>their bodilie eye is full of adultery, and cannot ceaſe to ſinne. 2. Pet.</hi> 2. 14.<note place="margin">2. Pe. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The light of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> which is the law of nature is extinguiſhed. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 28. Laſtly <hi>Faith,</hi> which is<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 2</note> the light of the ſoule is wholy blinded, for ſuch cannot ſee to take hold of the mercies of God, nor to apprehend his comfortable promiſes. <hi>Ebre.</hi> 4. 2. Now if the <hi>Eye,</hi> which is the light<note place="margin">Ebr. 4. 2.</note> of the body. if <hi>Reaſon,</hi> which is the light of the minde, if <hi>Faith</hi> which is the light of the ſoule be dimmed: <hi>If all that light which ſhould bee in vs, bee darkneſſe. Iuſtiſſima poena, vt qui ſciens</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Aug. de. li <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> be. arbit. lib. 3.</note> 
                        <hi>rectum non facit, amittat ſcire quod rectum:</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>) it is a puniſhment that hee (who knowing) doth not well, at length ſhould looſe the knowledge of wel dooing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo is it with the <hi>Hardned (as Iob.</hi> ſaith) <hi>The light of the vngodly</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iob. 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>ſhall bee darkened, and the wicked ſhall become blind</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Zeph. 1. 1</note> 
                        <hi>becauſe they haue ſinned againſt the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:43"/>The iudgement of the minde beeing thus peruerted, and Faith, which in all ſtormes and temptations ſhould guide the ſterne being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne, there fellowes a generall ſhipwrack of conſcience.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The word of God,</hi> is ſaid to bee ſharper then a<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>br. 4. 12.</note> two edged ſword, it pierceth the very ſinewes &amp; marrow, it <hi>diuideth the ſoule and ſpirit aſunder:</hi> how wonderfull it is in operation, how mightie to conuince our thoughts, howe powerfull to quicken the ſoule; how comfortable to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then our faith; I doubt not but moſt here, to their endleſſe comfort, do effectually know. This word, this mighty word, which for the piercing operation is reſembled to fire able to ſoften yron, this word it cannot mollifie the <hi>hardened.</hi> But as the bright beames of Sunne doe <hi>harden</hi> clay, and ſoften wax: and as the ſweete drops of raine do mollifie earth and <hi>harden</hi> ſand: ſo the heauenly and eternall word returneth not in vaine, but (by reaſon of different diſpoſition in the ſubiect) it illuminateth, it melteth the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, it obdurates and <hi>Hardens</hi> the wicked, <hi>their</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Eſay. 6. 9.</note> 
                        <hi>heartes being fat, their eyes heauie, and their eares ſhut, they ſhall heare indeed, but ſhall not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, they ſhall ſee and not perceiue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Where the word of God cannot preuaile there can be no repentance. It is true. The ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:180996:43"/>
ſaith, <hi>at what time ſoeuer a ſinner doth repent</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Eze. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>him of his ſin, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bottom of his hart. God wil put all his wickednes out off his remembrance.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon many take their pleaſure &amp; glut themſelues in ſin, &amp; at laſt they thinke to make all good by repentance. Indeed it is true, if they can repent: but they muſt obſerue what S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Qui promittit paenitenti veniam, non promittit peccanti paenite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiam.</hi> God, who promiſeth vnto euery one<note place="margin">Aug.</note> that repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth forgiuenes, doth not promiſe vnto euery one that ſinneth repentance. Repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance is the gift of god, &amp; ſuch as are <hi>hardened,</hi> becauſe in times paſt they deſpiſed the riches of his bounty &amp; grace, his long ſuffering &amp; mercy, that did cal them to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance, when they wold they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not repent. <hi>Ro.</hi> 2. 5. <hi>after hardnes, the heart it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> If there can be no repentance: then lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; teares are bootleſſe. Teares, they are the bloud of the ſoule, and the <hi>Wine of Angels,</hi> moſt<note place="margin">Bern.</note> pleaſing and acceptable in the ſight of God. Yet the <hi>hardened,</hi> though they ſhould waſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in their owne teares, it will not preuaile. <hi>Nihil proſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lamenta, ſi replicantur peccata:</hi> tears are not accepted, where ſinnes are ſtill and againe dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>Ebr.</hi> 12. 17. <hi>Eſau found no place to repentance</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ebr. 12. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>though he ſought the bleſſing with teares.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The holy &amp; bleſſed Sacraments now preſently to be adminiſtred, are <hi>Pledges</hi> of Gods loue, and <hi>Seals</hi> of our ſaluation. By Baptiſme <hi>he breaks the</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:44"/>
                        <hi>heads of the Dragons in the Waters: et per Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum coeli ianua aperitur.</hi> And by baptiſme euen the dore of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſet open. The ſacrament of the <hi>Lords ſupper,</hi> it is <hi>canalis gratiae, et lauacru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> l. 74. 14</note> the coduit of grace, &amp; the bath of the ſoule. What can be more ioyful, then by receiuing the ſigne of the croſſe, to fight vnder the banner of Chirſts loue, &amp; to be knit into the miſticall body of his ſaints? what can be more ioyful then to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that pure &amp; princely blood, the leaſt drop wherof being able to redeeme a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d worlds, I may reſt aſſured it is a full &amp; perfect ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for all my ſinnes? ſo that if my body hath ſinned, his body hath made ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, if my ſoule haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, his ſoule hath made recompence: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both ſoule and body are his, and ſo we firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fully ſetled in a Chriſtian ioy for euer.</p>
                     <p>Theſe holy and heauenly Sacraments are not effectuall in the obſtinate. <hi>Iudas</hi> notwithſtanding he was a diſciple of our Sauiour, and that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hand (which after for his ſake was nayled on the Croſſe) did reach him the bread of life: yet he was ſo hardened with ſecret ſin, &amp; a trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous diſpoſition: that as ſoone as he receiued the ſop, the deuilentred into him, tooke ful poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> h. 13. 27.</note> of him, &amp; ſo brought him to a moſt feareful end. Prayer, what maruailous things it hath brought to paſſe? and indeede what greater comfort can there be to a diſtreſſed minde, then to open our
<pb facs="tcp:180996:44"/>
griefe, to poure out our complaints, and eaſe our wounded hearts, by making our mone vnto God, by faithful and humble prayer: yet in thoſe that are <hi>Hardenedned, prayers</hi> of themſelues are fruteleſſe. Ioh. 9. 31. <hi>God heareth not the prayer of ſinners:</hi> that is, of ſuch as reteine a will to ſinne. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that enclineth his heart vnto wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſse,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pſa. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>God will not heare his prayers.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To hope in the prayer of others, that alſo is in vaine. Ier. 7. 16. <hi>Becauſe you haue done theſe things, and I ſpake vnto you, &amp; you would not heare, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ier. 7. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 11. 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>thou ſhalt not pray for this people, nor lift vp, cry, nor entreat me, for I wil not heare: Though Noe &amp; Iob, ſhould intreat me, though Moſes and Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el ſhould pray vnto me, yet will I not heare neither be intreated.</hi> In the 15. of the Prou. &amp; 15. <hi>it is ſaid a good conſcience is a continuall feaſt.</hi> Aſſuredly, if a man haue all earthly bleſſings, which his heart can deſire, if he wax neuer ſo warme and weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, yet if hee be at war with himſelfe, if hee be ſtung with the guilt of his owne thoughts, what comfort, what ioy can he haue?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The ſpirit of a man may beare his ſicknes, or infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pro. 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>but a wounded co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience who is able to endure?</hi> Contrariwiſe, peace with God, peace of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and quiet reſt of ſoule, it is the greateſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort that man can enioy vpon earth. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> calles it. <hi>The beautiful Temple of Salomon, the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Paradice, the golden bed of reſt, the ioye of the</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:45"/>
                        <hi>Angels, the treaſure of the great King, the mercie ſeat of the Cherubins, and the tabernacle of the holy Ghoſt.</hi> This peace the <hi>Hardened</hi> can neuer bee partakers of. <hi>Their grief is doubled with mourning,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>. 11. 10.</note> 
                        <hi>and remembring things paſt:</hi> and it is plainely ſaid, <hi>There is no peace vnto the wicked.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hope is the treaſurie of all ſpirituall and heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>. 48. 22.</note> 
                        <hi>bleſsings,</hi> in all wants and miſeries, it is the ſafe and ſure anchor of the Soule. <hi>For by hope wee are ſaued:</hi> but the hope of the vngodly is <hi>like the duſt blowne away with the wind. They forecaſt vnto</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>ſ. 17. 10.</note> 
                        <hi>themſelues cruel things, and their thoughts are like the flights of a bloudie and vanquiſht field, where al hope and comfort lyeth ſlaine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now when the ſoule thus affected, is not at peace with God, but giuen ouer to ſin, remaines in the ſtate of Condemnation, all temporall bleſſings, which are comforts to Gods children, they doe increaſe our condemnation.</p>
                     <p>Riches (weeknow) are the good bleſſings of God. but, to ſuch as haue no ſinne in their conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience: otherwiſe, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith in his 15, Chap. 27. <hi>If his face be ſo couered with fat, and that hee hath ſuch collups in his flancks, that in aboundance and proſperitie he forgets God, Dat legitimum, ſed non ſanctum vſum,</hi> he giueth a lawfull and outward, but not a ſanctified vſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sleepe</hi> is ſweet vnto euery man: but a mind ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded with ſin, is afflicted with feareful<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> iſ. 12. 13</note>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:45"/>
dreames and viſions in the night. <hi>The wicked that haue liued a diſſolute life, they are tormented with their owne imaginations,</hi> as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>The ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of God do fight againſt them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mirth and Cheerefulnes,</hi> the wiſe man ſaith: <hi>they are the reioycing of the heart, and prolonging of the life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Iob</hi> 14. 22. <hi>The ſinner while his fleſh is vpon him, he ſhall be ſorrowfull, while the ſoule is in him, he ſhall not ceaſe to mourne:</hi> Prouerbes 14. 13. <hi>Euen in laughing the heart is ſorrowfull, and the end of that mans mirth is heauineſſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now, if the eſtate of the <hi>Hardened</hi> be ſuch, that the light of the minde and ſoule be wholly dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, if the word of God cannot peirce the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing made ſhipwrack of conſcience, their heart it cannot repent, and ſo neither <hi>Sacraments,</hi> nor teares be auaileable. If their own Praiers cannot be heard, &amp; others are forbid to pray for them: if their ſleepe be feareful, theirlaughing inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mournfull, their riches curſings, their hope vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly forlorne, &amp; they can neuer enioy any peace of conſcience or quiet reſt of ſoule, iudge you, whether it had not bin better ſuch a man had not beene borne, or being borne had preſently bin flung into the bottome of the ſea, &amp; drowned in euerlaſting forgetfulnes. For (alas) when God is become our enimy, who is able to enter into co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, to match with the wrath of the Lord of hoſtes? whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a mans ownhart doth conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne him,
<pb facs="tcp:180996:46"/>
who is able to put to ſilence the voice of deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration? Oh happy is he that ſinneth leaſt, next he that returneth ſooneſt, but moſt dreadfull is the eſtate of him, who like <hi>Pharao</hi> is giuen ouer vnto <hi>Hardening.</hi> For he that is once come to this paſſe that as <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> he hath ſold himſelfe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit ſin, <hi>his minde reprobate, his conſeience ſeared, and</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>. 1. 28.</note> 
                        <hi>his ſoule frozen in the dregges of ſin,</hi> then though<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> im. 4. 2</note> he weepe &amp; lament with <hi>Eſau,</hi> though he would<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> h. 1. 12</note> reſtore that which hee hath wrongfully gotten with <hi>Iudas,</hi> though he do gird himſelfe in ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, &amp; walke ſoftly as <hi>Ahab,</hi> though he do pul the men of God to comfort him, and pray for him as <hi>Saul</hi> did; though hee do mourne like a Doue, and chatter like a crane, with the Pellica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though he do ſend forth ſhril and fearefull cries into the ayre, yet al this wil not helpe, (wo alas) there is no recouery, Ier 13. 23. <hi>Can the black-More</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>. 13. 23.</note> 
                        <hi>change his skin, or the Leopard his ſpots, then may they doe good, who haue accuſtomed themſelues to doe euilt?</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>He that</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>ſt. eth 7 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 7.</note> 
                        <hi>hardeneth his heart can neuer be cured. Habituati</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>ſ. 12. 10</note> 
                        <hi>in malo ſunt impaenituri, their thoughts can neuer</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> l. 17. 14</note> 
                        <hi>be altered: their ſtony hearts ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not become fleſhy, they</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> b. 10. 26</note> 
                        <hi>haue denied the power of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they haue deſpited</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> b. 12. 17</note> 
                        <hi>the ſpirit of grace, and though they ſeeke the bleſsing with tears, they can find no place to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance.</hi> This is a lamentable eſtate, this is a feareful iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for man to be left vnto himſelfe, giuen vp to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,
<pb facs="tcp:180996:46"/>
&amp; to be forſaken of God for euer, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate the Lord for his endleſſe mercy deliuer vs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The Remedie.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O eſchue this gulfe, and to auoide the danger of this <hi>Hardening,</hi> either we muſt cut off and ſtay the courſe of ſin in the act, or elſe we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt it in the beginning, and ſtay it in our thoughts. It is an excellent ſaying of S. <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom. Ibi maxime oportet obſeruare peccatum, vbi naſci solet:</hi> both in ſin, &amp; alſo in curing the diſeaſes of the body, it is the chiefeſt point, to obſerue &amp; finde out where the malady firſt tooke beginning. It is plaine, ſin firſt buddeth in the thought, and therupon S. <hi>Ierome</hi> calls it <hi>primo genita Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boli,</hi> the Diuels darling or firſt begotten. Sathan dare not atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt any vnto murther, treaso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or any ſuch grieuous ſin; vnleſſe he ſend an euil thought before, to trie whether he ſhall be welcome.</p>
                     <p>The Philiſtins will not venture, till <hi>Dalilah</hi> hath wrought the feat: as ſhe with <hi>Sampſon</hi> neuer left fawning, and creeping into his boſome, til by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting vnto her; he loſt both his ſtrength, &amp; his eyes, &amp; became a mil-horſe for the Philiſtins: ſo il thoughts allure &amp; toll on, ſo long, til the light of the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding being blinded, ſatan, that foule Philiſtine ſets them ſuch a griſt to grind as they muſt pay the loſſe of eternal life for the toll.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:47"/>The <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſayd truely <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, cuſtome ariſeth of very ſmall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings, and though it ſeeme a ſmall matter to lend the diuel an euill thought, yet the wiſe man ſaith in the 13. of <hi>Wiſ. Euill thoughts ſeparate from</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> rd.</note> 
                        <hi>God: cogitationes malae, dum ludunt illudunt:</hi> euill thoughts, while they dally, they doe deceiue. As the ſtream in the riuer <hi>Iordan</hi> doth carry the fiſh<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> hus.</note> ſwimming &amp; playing, til on a ſodaine they fall <hi>in mare mortuum</hi> into the dead ſea; where, by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of brimſtone they preſently die. ſo, many ſuffer themſelues to bee caried away ſo long with viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thoughts, &amp; wicked imaginations, that on a ſodain, the powers of the mind be grieuouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. The eye is <hi>feneſtra mentis,</hi> &amp; many times<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 9. 21.</note> ere euer we be aware, <hi>death ſtealeth in at the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow.</hi> The eare, <hi>Iob</hi> calleth it in his 12. Chap. the taſter of the ſoule: <hi>As the mouth taſteth meat for</hi>
                        <note place="margin">12. 11.</note> 
                        <hi>the belly: ſo the eare taſteth words for the ſoule.</hi> He that hath a wicked eye, and an vnchaſt eare (as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith of <hi>Simon Magus</hi>) his ſoule will ſoone<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> um <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> guae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> um.</note> be brought to the gall of bitterneſſe. Therfore, wiſe men may hereby iudge, how carefully, how prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly the educatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of youth (eſpecially of the nobler ſort) ought to be reſpected. How flattering paraſits &amp; prophane ieſters ought to<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> ld this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> nſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> be warily ſhuned. Alas, the mind &amp; diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of youth, at the firſt, it is like a ſweet and brightſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer diſh you may put in what you pleaſe: but if
<pb facs="tcp:180996:47"/>
through vile <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> &amp; diſſolute company, the affection be once led away, &amp; the diſpoſition in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, wo worth that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, for the infectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of<note place="margin">Iob. 36. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> ſin taken in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der yeares: <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>The ſoule dieth in youth:</hi> as cloth ſtained in the wooll, doth neuer loſe the colour, ſo the ſtaine of ſin taken in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der yeares wil hardly or neuer be taken out: nay, that which afterwards, diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; yeares doth know and iudge in it ſelfe moſt hatefull, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <note place="margin">Chriſoſt.</note>. By e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill cuſtome, hee is inforced to put the ſame in practiſe whether he will or no. In the 9. of <hi>Mark.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1. ver. the foule ſpirit which kept poſſeſſion fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a child, could not bee caſt out by any other but only by our Sauiour. <hi>Iob</hi> made a couenant with his heart, &amp; <hi>Dauid</hi> praied the lord to turne away his eyes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beholding vanity. Euery good man ought to labour &amp; ſtriue with himſelf, to quench his deſires, to checke his thoughts, to beat down &amp; keepe vnder his affections, that though he do ſin ſometimes of infirmity, yet it may neuer ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally infect the minde: it may neuer be ſetled in the thought. There is no ſacrifice more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto God, then the nipping of a ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts head: therfore, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh, or the children of <hi>Babilon, adpetras illidere;</hi> to daſh their braines<note place="margin">Pſal. 137. 9</note> againſt the wall, while they are yong: ſo the beſt way to preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Hardening,</hi> is to nip ſin in the head at the firſt, to kil the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of it in our thoughts.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:48"/>Now if God do not ſo ſtrengthen vs to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſin in the thought, the next way to ſhunne this <hi>Hardening</hi> is to ſtay the courſe of it in the act. <hi>For God wil wound the heary ſcalpe of ſuch, as go</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> l. 68. 22<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>on ſtill in their wickednes. Paruus error in principio maximus eſt in fine,</hi> A ſmall ſcape in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning many times proues a miſchiefe in the end. <hi>Conſuetudo peccandi tollit ſenſum peccati.</hi> The cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of ſin takes away all feeling of ſin, as hee that is ſtung with a viper, is ſo deadly benu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med, that he feeles the ſting of nothing els: ſo he that hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a cuſtome of offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, neuer feeles the infectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any ſin, though it rancle neuer ſo grieuouſly. In the 69. Pſ. 16. ver. <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth, <hi>O let not the pitſhut her mouth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me,</hi> To ſin is to fal into a pit, but to take a cuſtom in ſin, is to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the pit &amp; da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it vp, that we ſhal neuer get out againe. <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuetudine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vincere dura pugna</hi> (ſaith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi>)<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> ag. in ſal. 36.</note> It is a difficult fight to ouercome cuſtome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for in all humane things <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, cuſtome is the moſtintollerable tirant. <hi>Horatius</hi> the <hi>Romane<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> being to fight with 3. enimies at once, did ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle them out, &amp; then ſlew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one by one: ſo the force of ſin is to be cut off in euery ſeueral actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> ro. 28. 26</note> leaſt by gathering ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth it ourthrow vs. <hi>He that truſteth his owne heart is not wiſe.</hi> In this caſe it is good for a man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o ſuſpect his owne heart, to call his own way to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance, to take ſomtimes a ſuruey &amp; a view of the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of his life, &amp; dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:180996:48"/>
actions, &amp; if he find in himſelf, that God hath ſuffered him ſo far to be tempted: that he is falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into any foule offence, which he knowethis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly both againſt God, &amp; his own conſcience, then preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to beſtir himſelf, neuer to ſuffer his eies to ſleep, nor his eie-lids to ſlu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, til he haue poured out his heart vnto God, made bitter la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation; craued pardon with repentance, and vowed by Gods aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce neuer to offend in any ſuch ſort againe. Otherwiſe, if lightly he paſſe it ouer, &amp; ſo go on: as <hi>Mithridates</hi> accuſtomed his body ſo much to the receipt of poyſon, that at length no poiſon would work on him, ſo he that hath once taken in with the cuſtom of ſin, ſhal at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth come to that paſſe, that the greateſt ſin that<note place="margin">Aug. in ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n adu. Dom.</note> is, he ſhall neuer feele it. <hi>Omne peccatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vileſcit co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudine, et ſit homini quaſinullu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> the greateſt ſin by cuſtom comes to be accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted nothing. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body is ſore hurt &amp; wounded, there is no dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of time, but preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly it muſt be looked to: ſo when the ſoule is wounded, we muſt not defer to turne vnto the Lord, but flie to him with impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate prayer, with a broken &amp; mourning heart, for feare the wound do feſter inwardly, and ſo there be no recouery. I make it plaine by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thus. If a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>take in the ſpring 3. or 4. plants, and ſet them al together at one time, if he come by and by, or within a while after, he may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pull vp one of them: if he ſtay a fortnight, or
<pb facs="tcp:180996:49"/>
a moneth, he may pull vp an other, but it will be ſomewhat harder, if he ſtay a yeare or two, till it ſettle and take roote, then he may pul and ſtraine his very heart ſtrings, but his labour is loſt, hee ſhall neuer be able to pull it vp. One ſin, one of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, if we labour to pul it vp in time, it may be forgiuen, it may be taken away; if we let it go on to two or three, with vnfained repentance, with bleeding teares, with vnceſſant outcryes vnto a gratious God, they may be raſed out and wiped away, but with greater difficulty: at length, if a man giue ouer himſelfe vnto ſinne, ſo that it take deepe roote in the heart, and bee ſetled in the ſoule, he ſhall neuer be able to pull it vp, nor to ariſe from the death of ſinne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:180996:49"/>
                     <head>Application.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O draw then to an end: foraſmuch as God deſireth not the death of any ſinner, but moſt louingly offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his grace &amp; meanes of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto all: ſeeing ſinne doth proced from our owne vile concupiſcence, and we neuer ſtriuing to ſtay the courſe of it in our thoughts, do ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall away: ſeeing by degrees, againſt their own knowledge, men do wound their ſoules with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny actuall ſinnes, and thervpon God doth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his grace, and ſo forſake them; and this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking is ſuch a forlorne eſtate, that as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith: 12. 14. <hi>God ſhutteth a man vp, and he can neuer be looſed:</hi> O how feruent ought we to be in prayer, thereby to kindle in vs, the heat of Gods ſpirit? how deuout in ſweete &amp; heauenly meditations, to ſtir vp in vs the good graces of God? how di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent to ſhewe the fruits of our faith, euer ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the workes &amp; labours of our calling; gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no aduantage to our aduerſary? how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, when wee heare the word of God, to do it with a humble ſpirit, with great reuerence? ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to keepe a tender heart, a minde and cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that may eaſily bee touched with remorſe: how deſirous &amp; ſecretly ioyfull at this holy time to prepare our ſelues to the receiuing of the
<pb facs="tcp:180996:50"/>
bleſſed ſacraments, to haue our hearts ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped off worldly vanities, to cal home our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, to appeaſe our thoughts, and ſo peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to bath our ſoules afreſh in the precious blood of our euerlaſting redeemer. That ſo feeling our ſelues as it were newely created a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, ſoule &amp; body, heart, hand &amp; tongue, may neuer ceaſe to ſound praiſes vnto him, who doth neuer ceaſe to renew his mercies vnto vs.</p>
                     <p>The holy &amp; kingly Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> he is a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy example for this roial preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſet him before your eies, &amp; obſerue the whole courſe of his life How ſweet and mild was his ſpirit in forbearing to take reuenge for himſelfe? how couragious &amp; inuincible his faith, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſtood in the quarrel of gods honour? how dearly affected to his people, when he ſaid to the deſtroying <hi>Angel, not theſe ſheep, but it is I that haue offended?</hi> what melting &amp; kinde affection did he ſhew towards <hi>Ionathan,</hi> &amp; thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he loued? what a mournful &amp; repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t heart, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he knew that he had offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded? how full of diuine meditations to better his thoughts? how frequent in praier, falling fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual ſtreame? how ioyfull in Gods ſeruice, <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing before the Ark?</hi> how reuerend in Gods houſe <hi>kneeling &amp; bowing</hi> in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple before al the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? what a thankfull heart <hi>in offering to build a glorious temple to the Lord?</hi> what an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble minde ſaying, <hi>what am</hi> I, &amp; <hi>what was my fathers houſe,</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:180996:50"/>
                        <hi>that thou haſt brought vs hitherto?</hi> what a <hi>chary &amp; tender care of Gods glory,</hi> wherſoeuer he became? how abundant in praiſes &amp; thankſgiuing, calling euery member of himſelfe, &amp; all the creatures both of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; earth to make one quire in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth, ſinging, &amp; ſounding the euerlaſting praiſes of his God? But why did <hi>Dauid</hi> thus? to what end was al this? that he might be ſure ſtil <hi>to hold faſt by God,</hi> to be intirely knit vnto him, by al means poſsible to retaine his loue, for feare leaſt God hauing raiſed him to the height of renowne deliuered him miraculouſly out off many emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and bloudy dangers, &amp; ſo ſet a crowne of bleſſings vpon his head: if <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhould haue ſhowne any vnthankfulnes, any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt, or the leaſt neglect of his loue, a mighty &amp; ielous god, he alſo, vpon iuſt cauſe might haue withdrawne his loue, &amp; laid al his honour in the duſt againe.</p>
                     <p>Now therfore, with al humbleneſſe &amp; duety, I intreat you, by the tender mercies of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, &amp; in the name of the liuing God I chalenge euery chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which hopes for any ioy in the life to come, take heed of actuall and preſumptuous ſinnes, in no caſe let them <hi>haue dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer you,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 19. 1</note> do not wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d your ſoules as <hi>Pharao</hi> did, with wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full offences againſt your own knowledge try &amp; examine all your thoughts, how &amp; wherin they ſtand affected, &amp; aboue al grieue not the bleſſed motions of that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable ſpirit, which keepes
<pb facs="tcp:180996:51"/>
the very <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Being</hi> of the ſoule. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, let al ſlaunderous mouthes be ſtopped, &amp; all the factious ſciſmatiques in the land aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, in beholding your chriſtian and Princely example: continue ſtill to be louingly and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected one towards another: celebrate this holy time in a true religious maner. Sanctifie the ioyful beginning of this new yeares raine with new deuotion vnto God: lay all your <hi>Honors</hi> downe at the foote of the <hi>altar:</hi> receiue the holy Sacraments ioyntly together, and ſo bee faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully knit in loue and in one head <hi>Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> go cheerefully on, delight ſtill in doing good: &amp; the <hi>Lord God</hi> of our Fathers increaſe in you good deſires, giue you zeale to performe them, confirme vnto you, &amp; to your ſeede, all his good promiſes, and vnto euery one of vs here graunt pardon for offences paſt, giue vs comfort and ſtrength in temptations to come, change all our liues more and more to a better courſe, euen for his bleſſed Sonne <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> ſake: who with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and prayſed for euer.</p>
                     <closer>Amen.</closer>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180996:51"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
